Aloha everybody and welcome to the Jason
Jones Show. I am your host Jason Jones
broadcasting from an undisclosed
location somewhere in the outskirts of
Chicago. My guest today is former CIA
officer John Kiriakou, whistleblower,
American hero, legend, um the Gen Z
whisperer. We have a great interview and
I want to get right to it. Before we do,
I just want to let you know this show is
being brought to you by the Vulnerable
People Project standing in solidarity
with the most vulnerable people in the
world when the world has walked away.
Just this week we saw increased violence
in Nigeria, Christians being kidnapped,
attacks on churches in Chad. In fact,
the VPP through our vulnerable parish
program has just begun securing more
parishes in Nigeria. We're up to 54
parishes secured. We added a parish in
in in Chad. We documented and it
received international coverage
including the Vatican News, Haaretz, and
other news sources,
uh violent IDF attack on the community
in Taybeh. They came in with stun gun
stun grenade,
uh
drones, armored vehicles. We documented
it. If you want to be a part of this
campaign to defend vulnerable
communities
from the West Bank
to China to Darfur, go to
vulnerablepeopleproject.com,
look around and see the work that we do.
All right? Now, on to my interview with
the legend
John Kiriakou on the Jason Jones Show.
John Kiriakou, welcome to the Jason
Jones Show.
>> Thank you very much. Good to be with you
again.
>> It's good to see you.
>> Good to see you as always.
>> And the first time we met, you were in a
different place than you are right now.
>> Yeah.
>> You were a much different place and and
I was with my filmmaking partner and you
were you were talking to us about maybe
we could make your film and we said no
way. This is so much bigger than us.
It's the perfectly crafted hero's
journey. Your story is the hero's
journey by the book. It's the writer's
structure of the story.
Ordinary world, call to adventure,
threshold guardians, innermost cave,
death and resurrection, return to the
ordinary world. Like you've lived it
perfectly. And so here we are on the
other side.
Um so it's not a lot of people in
history
who have suffered what you suffered have
the privilege in their lifetime to
experience the resurrection. They may be
resurrected in the history books.
Um have you thought about that? Like
just what it's like to have gone through
all of that and get to live through your
redemption.
>> I like to think that all of that is
true.
I like to think.
Um and I'm I'm confident that
I'm on the right side of this issue. I
I've been on the right side of it from
the very beginning. It's been a long
journey. And I'll tell you, you really
get to see who your friends and
supporters are. And sometimes
sometimes the people who are the
quickest to turn on you
are the ones that you're laying next to
in bed at night. You just never know.
People make funny decisions.
And um
you have to be supremely confident that
you're right and that everybody else is
wrong.
I've been called
arrogant, narcissistic by people close
to me because I just would not stop
talking about these issues and insisting
that I was on the right side of it.
And in in the end I think I've been
vindicated. I think I have been on the
right side of it. Um I don't know why it
was so confusing to everybody else.
You know, when it comes down to the
basic issue of of torture,
it just seems so clear-cut to me.
I don't understand why it wasn't
clear-cut to everybody else.
And uh I've just decided to to go with
it and accept that this is this is the
this is the plan that God had for me.
It's certainly not what I expected. I
really believed that I would work my 30
years at the CIA, I'd retire on a
Friday, on Monday I would start up with
some intelligence community contractor,
I'd have a little house at the beach
with my wife and kids and live happily
ever after. I really believed that for
many years and that wasn't to be at all.
And so
here I am all these years later
um went to prison for a couple of years,
have friends who are like nationally
known mobsters
or nationally known
political leaders
and I embraced all of it.
>> Yeah, the the the the spectrum of people
who have admired you and reached out to
you is it's unbelievable. It's the the
whole spectrum.
>> It's crazy, you know.
>> Susan Sarandon to Tucker Carlson and
everything in between. What do they
share what do they have in common?
The the mobsters, Susan Sarandon, Tucker
Carlson, all the people that stood by
your side. What is the gesture line that
they all have in common?
>> a really great question and I think that
and this is going to sound a little bit
crazy, but it's it's all about
transparency and truth telling. One of
the things I mean it's easy to say, you
know, Susan Sarandon, she's a well-known
truth teller. She's demonstrating in the
streets all the time for, you know,
human rights and civil rights and civil
liberties and all that stuff. Yoko Ono
is another one. Um
uh
>> [laughter]
>> I know, it's crazy, right?
>> Uh Roger Waters, the lead guitarist from
uh Pink Floyd, paid off my second
mortgage so that my my wife didn't lose
our house when I went to prison and did
it anonymously.
It was 7 years before I learned it was
Roger that paid off my mortgage.
>> That's unbelievable.
>> It's crazy.
Um but then, you know, these mob figures
just gravitated toward me.
And it was because I told the truth and
called the government on the carpet. And
so
there is this theme that even though
even though we may disagree on 99% of
the other issues, on that one core issue
we're all in alignment. And I found that
to be the one consistent theme.
>> Tre
respecting people enough to be honest.
>> Yeah. You don't have to agree on
everything. You don't have to have
friends that
you know, there's this prerequisite that
you have to agree on every issue to be
friends.
I don't think I agree with everybody or
on every issue with anybody in the
world.
So why would that be a prerequisite?
You know, we can respect each other
and respect differences in opinion
and you know, live happily ever after.
It's just become obvious to me the the
older that I get.
>> It's powerful. I want to
do the hero's journey with you. When we
start from the beginning, interviewing
you is is nerve-racking. It's It's like
going on a date with someone who you're
like, "Have you been on many dates
recently?" Well, yeah, I went out with
Brad Pitt and then it was like Tom
Cruise and then it's like, "Yeah, I've
been interviewed by Theo Von, by Joe
Rogan, by Tucker Carlson." That's That's
scary.
>> May I actually interrupt you on that
point?
>> This little
vignette is apropos of of this
lead-in.
So I got divorced in 2018.
I waited a couple of years, decided to
go on the apps.
So I figured I'm going to go to Bumble
cuz Bumble is supposed to be the the
ladies' app.
>> app, yeah.
>> The gentleman's app because the woman
chooses who she wants to talk to. Okay.
I go. I see this absolutely stunning
woman. I swipe right. She swipes right.
I said, "Hey, I matched."
So we start texting back and forth.
And we agree to meet for a glass of
wine.
So, we meet in person. I said, "My God,
she's even more beautiful than in her
pictures."
But, I wanted to be transparent. So, I
said, "Listen, before this goes
anywhere, you should know something
about me. And if you don't like it, you
can walk, and no hard feelings at all."
She says, "No, I know who you are, Mr.
Kyriacou." I had never told her my last
name.
So, I said, "Oh, okay. So, you're okay?"
And she said, "Yeah, you should know
something about me." I said, "Great."
She says, "I'm the Deputy Assistant
Secretary of State for Human Rights."
And I said, "Hey, then we're a match.
Great, right?"
>> Yeah.
>> So, I had such a good time. I said,
"Please go out with me Saturday night.
We'll have dinner." Great. We went out,
had a great time. And I said,
"Let's do a little day trip next
weekend." I've always wanted to go to
Shepherdstown, West Virginia. It's about
an hour and 15 minutes away. Civil War
town, art galleries, boutiques. She
says, "Great." I said, "Great. I'll pick
you up 10:00 Saturday morning."
I go to her house. I pick her up.
She gets in my car. I said, "Good
morning." She says,
"Good morning."
I was like, "Oh, doggone it."
I said, "What's wrong?" "Nothing."
"Nothing." I said, "Come on, let's not
play these games. Obviously, clearly,
something's wrong. What is it?"
She says,
"I have doubts about your left-wing
credentials."
I said, "Excuse me? I went to prison for
my left-wing credentials.
What's your problem?" She said, "I saw a
YouTube video in which you quoted Ronald
Reagan."
And I said, "Yeah. I know what the quote
is. I said, 'Ronald Reagan was right
when he said that government is the
problem.
It's not the solution to the problem.'
He's right."
She says, "I just need to process this."
I said, "Fine." We go to Shepherdstown,
had a terrible time. It's about 3:00 in
the afternoon, it starts to rain very
hard. I said, "Let's go back to DC."
We get back in my car.
I don't like sitting on my cell phone in
the car, so I take my phone out, I put
it in the cup holder next to me. Soon as
I start driving, I get a text message.
It goes
So, I look down and I said, "Oh, no."
It's from Tucker Carlson.
>> [laughter]
>> And it says, "Hey, buddy, haven't heard
from you in a while. Are you free for a
beer this weekend?"
And I try to discreetly look at her
and I see she's looking right at the
phone. Oh, no. And she says,
"Do you know Tucker Carlson?"
And I said, "Yes, and he's a lovely
man."
And she says, "Take me home right now
and don't ever call me again."
And so I did.
And it just made me realize even more
clearly that I'm right.
>> Yes.
>> We don't have to agree on everything to
respect one another and to respect one
another's points of view.
>> You know, when we were young,
there was left liberal and right
liberal. At the end, we all believed in
freedom of speech,
>> freedom of religion, free economy.
>> And our differences on foreign policy
ended at the shore, we used to say.
>> And it was but that's now I feel like
the left is illiberal and the right is
illiberal.
We've lost a belief in the founding
principles of our republic on both the
left and the right.
>> And that's why I find myself
in
Excuse me, in agreement so often with
with people who call themselves MAGA
Republicans.
Because and I've said this many times, I
don't believe that the ideological
spectrum is a straight line from left to
right. I believe that it's a circle
and it meets at a certain point and we
should embrace that meeting. We should
embrace the ability to cooperate and
work with each other and to respect each
other and each other's positions.
>> Yes,
I think sincere people on the left and
the right are ordered to the common
good. We disagree prudentially, but we
we're sincere people are striving for
the same things. But there are insincere
people and grifters also across the
ideological spectrum.
>> Absolutely. 100% and we see it every day
in the in the papers.
Absolutely true.
>> So with that,
I want to go back to the beginning. So
because I'm nervous to interview you is
you've been interviewed by the best
people, you've been asked the best
questions. You're my children's and
everyone under 20's hero. So I don't
want to mess this up. So I went to Jason
Rocket, our friend, who's a world-class
researcher who's worked on the most
important biographies of the 20th
century. Henry Kissinger's go-to guy.
>> Henry Kissinger's guy. So I said,
"What
should I ask John?"
He said, "Oh, that's simple. No one's
asked him. No one I've never seen it.
Ask him about his parents." And then I
saw you on
Theo Von this week.
>> Right.
>> Who I love that man's heart. He's such a
beautiful human being.
>> Yeah, really genuine genuine person.
>> Really, yeah, something special. To me,
the what gives me hope for America is
that America loves Theo Von.
>> Mhm.
>> And Tim Dillon and you. It's like, you
know what I mean? And not a lot in
common between you, Theo Von, and Tim
Dillon. But the fact that America,
especially Gen Z, loves you guys, I'm
like, okay, there's hope for this
country.
And but you were talking about Tulsi
Gabbard.
>> Mhm.
>> I've known Tulsi since she was 12. Her
father and mother were good friends of
mine. They're the most beautiful people
I've ever met in my life. They they love
each other so much.
Um in the in the in the '90s, her father
really led the campaign to protect
traditional marriage in Hawaii and he
was really hated and I was chairman of
the college Republicans at the time,
worked closely with him.
And I watched how and I was in Hawaii in
the army, but I was from Chicago. So I
was kind of a fiery young man.
Here's a Samoan man, her father.
And the way he responded to hatred was
always with joy, with kindness, with a
smile. I've never saw him angry. I never
saw him lose his temper.
And the way that those two are both, her
mom and her dad, are like these strong
individuals,
but they're a perfect couple. They don't
dominate each other. They're And they're
both warm. And I say to people, "If you
want to understand Tulsi Gabbard, you
cannot. She will never make sense to you
until you meet her parents." And so I
had Jason's text, "I'm watching you talk
about Tulsi." And I realized Jason was
right. That's the question.
The question is, "Where did John
Kiriakou come from? This guy that's like
Tulsi.
They don't make sense in this world."
So, that's the question. We want to know
about your mom and your dad.
>> Well, I appreciate that. Um I was
really, really fortunate growing up. My
parents were deeply in love with each
other. And they came from completely
I shouldn't say completely different
backgrounds. They came from different
backgrounds. First of all, all four of
my grandparents came from the island of
Rhodes in Greece.
My dad's parents came in 1931. My mom's
parents in 1934. And they were all
farmers in Greece.
Um
but my dad's parents stressed education
because they didn't have an education.
And it was just my dad and his sister.
Mom My mom's side, my mom had eight
brothers and sisters. And education was
never important on my mom's side of the
family. So, my dad got a PhD in um
in education.
And my mom ended up getting
a master's degree in in education. She
went to college when I was
when I started fifth grade,
she started college. And then she
finished grad school when I finished
grad school.
So, um
education was everything. They were both
in elementary ed. My mom was a third
grade teacher, my dad was an elementary
school principal for 44 years.
And they were deeply in love with each
other. To the point where my brother and
sister and I would be like, "Stop you
guys.
Get a room or something, you know?" And
I I grew up
thinking that everybody's family was
like that.
>> Mhm.
>> And it wasn't. They weren't. I I was
just very, very fortunate. When I was 9
years old,
I told my parents that I wanted to be a
spy when I grew up. And they thought it
was cute, and they bought me
walkie-talkies for Christmas, and
disappearing ink, and stuff like that.
My brother and I would walk around the
neighborhood like
spying on the neighbors.
>> [laughter]
>> We really did. But then when I was 16, I
told my dad, I still remember the
conversation. We were driving on Old
Plank Road, past Fraser's Pond,
and I said, "Dad, I want to be a spy in
the Middle East
when I when I finish college." And he
said, "Still with the spy thing?
Can't you like be a dentist or
something?" And I said, "No, I really
want to be a spy."
And he said, "Why the Middle East?"
And I said, "I don't know. It's just
fascinating to me."
And so,
I only applied
to George Washington University because
they had a degree uh program in Middle
Eastern studies,
and that's all I cared about. It's all I
wanted to study.
And
they didn't like it, but they supported
it because they knew that that's what I
wanted to do, that it would make me
happy.
>> Why don't you think they liked it?
>> They were afraid that something would
happen to me.
>> And they had no doubt if you They
weren't like, "Okay, this is just a
phase." They knew that you had your eye
set on it and you were probably going to
>> And then when I joined the CIA, and they
were happy and proud, and I said, "You
can't tell anybody." My dad like stands
up in church and announces
>> [laughter]
>> And I said to him, I said, "Dad, you're
going to get me killed. I'm undercover,
and you're just announcing to the church
and breaking my cover. He's like, "I'm
sorry. I'm sorry. I was so proud. I'm
sorry." I said, "Dad, you got to stop
doing that."
And he did. He stopped. But, um
But, I had only been on the job, I don't
know, 8 months. I've mentioned this in a
couple of podcasts.
I When I was hired into the CIA, I was I
was put on the Iraq desk.
And, um
I became Saddam Hussein's classified,
uh,
biographer for the intelligence
community. I was the only one covering
leadership analysis on the Iraqi
leadership. And so, when Iraq invaded
Kuwait, I got into the office very early
one morning, 6:00. Not one morning, that
morning, August 2nd, 1990.
And my boss said, um
"Don't take your jacket off. We're going
to the White House."
I had never been to the White House,
except as a tourist.
And so, we got in a car, went to the
White House. There's a Marine there
waiting for us. He escorts us into the
Oval Office.
I'm 25 years old.
It's the president, the vice president,
the national security advisor, and the
CIA director, and then my boss and me.
And
you know, you don't speak until you're
spoken to, and you don't sit until the
president tells you to sit. So, there's
two nice like wingback chairs for the
president and the vice president, two
like
less comfortable dining room kind of
chairs for the CIA director and the
national security advisor, and then the
couch where my boss and I sat down. And
the president says, "Gentlemen, sit.
Sit." So, we sit down.
And then he says,
"Well,
now what do we do?"
And then everybody turns and looks at
me.
And I'm looking at him like
I was speechless. And then it took me a
second. I said, "Oh, well, uh
Mr. President, as you know, Iraqi troops
crossed the border at 0200 this morning.
The royal family has fled to Saudi
Arabia, and blah blah blah blah blah.
And then
that night my parents called me.
And they said, "Busy day for you today,
huh?" And I said, "Yeah, it was a busy
day."
"Well, what was it like? What did you
do?" And I said, "Well, I I just I sat
at my desk and I wrote as much as I
could write."
>> You couldn't tell them.
>> Uh-uh.
>> Cuz dad had a big mouth.
>> Dad had a big mouth.
>> He's proud.
>> He's going to call everybody at church.
>> Next week on Sunday, everybody in
announcements and prayers at
>> Exactly.
Yeah, exactly. But they were proud of me
and
and supportive of me. And you know, we
just took it from there. He even came to
the Middle East to visit me, he and my
brother. Flew out to Bahrain. And then
we went to Qatar, and we went to Dubai
and Abu Dhabi at the same time.
He just wanted to get a
get a sense of things. And then when I
was assigned in Greece, they came to
Greece and visited me for a couple of
weeks there, too.
>> Did being Greek help you in your job,
like your heritage and sort of having a
cultural memory of the Ottoman Empire
and
>> Very, very much so.
Now, I'm I'm biased. You and I have
joked about this in the time that we've
known each other. Um yeah, I'm biased,
but yeah, it kind of gave me a
it kind of gave me a sense of purpose.
Yeah. The Ottomans Listen, I'm just
going to say it straight out. The
Ottomans had Greeks as slaves for 450
years.
They murdered the men. They sold the
women as slaves in Algiers. They
kidnapped the children and turned them
into what are called Janissaries,
training them, raising them as Turks,
training them as special forces um
soldiers, and then sending them back to
Greece to kill Greeks.
>> Yeah.
Malta was seized by Janissaries.
>> Malta was seized by Janissaries, as was
Rhodes, our ancestral island.
And um
you know,
this wasn't just part of
family lore. This was a reality. I have
pictures of my great-grandparents
wearing Turkish clothes because they
were forced to wear Turkish clothes.
Uh the Turks tried to snuff out the
Greek language and it was only in church
that we were able to keep the language
alive. And church wasn't even in church
anymore because most of the churches
were burned. They were in caves or in
private houses. And so there was this
sense of
you know, having your culture almost
snuffed out
that made me want to work even harder to
protect the culture that we have now.
I took it very seriously.
>> And you saw your Greek culture all over
the Middle East, right? In the Orthodox
church.
>> All over the Middle East. In fact, when
I was stationed in Bahrain
there was a very tight Greek community
there.
Greeks, Cypriots, Greek Americans, Greek
Canadians, Australians, British, anybody
who identified as Greek
we we had dinner parties and
different get-togethers. Everybody was
very successful. They were mostly
uh
builders, bankers, and um finally the
Archbishop of Cyprus
uh
said that he wanted to make a visit.
I became very close to the Bahraini
royal family. In fact, I'm still in
regular
you know, texting touch with the Crown
Prince. We went to college together.
We've been friends ever since.
And um
the Archbishop sends a cable saying he
wants to come to the island and visit.
Well, there were churches uh in Bahrain
but there's a Catholic church, there's
an Anglican church. There was no
Orthodox church. And so God bless him,
the Archbishop came and met with the
Emir and just came right out and said to
the Emir
that he would like it if very much if
the Emir would donate a plot of land so
we could build a church.
And the Emir said, "Done."
And as we were walking out of the
palace, the Emir said to me
"I like your Imam very much."
>> He called him the Imam.
>> And I said, "Your Highness, I think he
likes you very much."
And next thing you know, 10 months later
we've got a church.
And uh it became
no pun intended, it became a Mecca for
Orthodox, you know, in the Eastern
province of Saudi Arabia. You just drive
across the bridge and you can go to
church on Sundays.
It was a very, very big deal.
So, yeah, there There was a lot of that.
>> That story, and I want to get back to
your parents, but that story reminds me
of, you know, what's striking about you,
a lot of
um influencers, not that you're an
influencer, that were former Tier 1
operators or were in CIA,
they brand themselves. They wear
tactical watches. They have the shirts
sized too short, right? They wear hats
like I do with the bend. You could tell
I was in the infantry. Um so, maybe I'm
part of the problem, but but the way you
present yourself, it's just like a
winsome gentleman.
You know, and then but when we hear your
stories,
the other stories that we hear from
these guys, and no disrespect to their
service to our country, but they pale in
comparison. But, you still always
present yourself as this winsome
gentleman. Do you think Was that
something you cultivated
>> No.
>> to be That's just who you are.
Yeah, it's just who I am. I never
understood the desire
of my CIA contemporaries to be the
heavy.
I I never understood what they hoped to
accomplish.
And I'll give you an example. This is an
example that I I use when I speak to
business groups all the time, but I
think it's the clearest example.
When I was stationed in Pakistan, I got
a tip that
a group of mid-level Al-Qaeda
figures was meeting in an
Arab coffee shop
every day.
10:00 they'd go in and have coffee.
And so,
I bought an Arabic language newspaper
and I went to the coffee shop at 9:30
knowing they would come at 10:00.
And um
and I would just sit there.
And sure enough, at 10:00 that first day
they all came in, didn't pay any
attention to me, just went to their
table, sat and had coffee. I just sat
there and read the paper.
I did that every day for a week.
The second week, I'm in there again,
and one of them
looks at me and nods. And I nodded back
at him.
That went for another week.
The third week, as he's walking in, he
says to me, "As-salamu alaykum, may
peace be upon you." And I said, "Wa
alaykumu as-salam, and upon you peace."
And then one day he came in alone.
So I said, "Ijlis tafaddal, please sit
with me."
And he sits down, we start talking. I
said, "My name is Hassan." His name is
Muhammad. "Nice to meet you, Muhammad.
Where are you from?" He's from Egypt. He
said, "Where are you from?" "I'm from
Lebanon."
And um
I asked him how long he'd been there. He
said, "5 years." He's I said, "W- What
did you come for?" He said, "I came to
make jihad against the Americans.
But uh I'm tired." He said, "I came from
Afghanistan." He did say that he was
hiding in a cave, and we had fired a
cruise missile into the cave, and he
said he used the word hideous. It was
the most hideous explosion he had ever
heard, and when he came out he was
bleeding from the ears.
And he said he had had enough, and he
just wanted to go home.
And I said, "How's your family? You
never say how's your wife. That's very
rude."
>> Okay.
>> You say, "How's your family?
And what does your family say about it?"
And he said, "Alas," he said, "I haven't
seen my family in 5 years. I have a son
that I've never met. He's 5 years old. I
have a 9-year-old daughter, and I just
want to go home."
So I said, "Let me take you to lunch.
Let's talk about this more." So we go to
lunch.
And we're talking and talking and
talking.
And then the next day we meet again.
And finally I said to him,
"Ya Muhammad,
I haven't been completely honest with
you. I'm actually not Lebanese." And he
said, "Okay."
And I said, "I'm actually American."
"Okay."
I said, are you all right with that? And
he said, yeah, you have a little bit of
an accent.
I couldn't quite put my finger on. I
said, well, there's more to it. And I
don't want to frighten you, but I'm
actually a CIA officer.
And he says, okay.
He said, what do you want from me?
And I told him very specifically what I
wanted from him.
And he said, and what will you do for
me?
And I said, anything your heart desires.
I said, do you want to go home to see
your family?
I'll send you home with a bag of money
that'll weigh you down.
And you can start a whole new life.
And put all of this behind you. You
don't want to live here.
You want to be with your wife and your
children.
And start something new and build
something for your children.
And he accepted it.
And he gave me everything I wanted.
And I took him to the airport.
And I said, Muhammad, before you leave,
I want to ask you, why did you agree to
give me what I asked for?
You didn't run screaming from the room
when I told him who I was.
And he said, I've been here for 5 years.
And you're the first person who ever
asked me about my family.
And you know, it it crystallized
something in my mind.
It's that it's all about the
relationship. Success is all about the
relationship. Didn't cost me anything to
ask him about his family.
Just like it wouldn't cost,
you know, a partner at Deloitte, where I
used to work after I left the agency, to
ask the person in charge of the big
audit contract, how'd your kid do in the
in the Little League game? How's your
husband doing after his gallbladder
surgery? Hey, did you have a happy
birthday party last week? It doesn't
cost anything to take interest in
somebody's life and to treat them with
respect and kindness.
Can you imagine going up to to this guy
in the coffee shop and saying,
"You better give me what I want or I'm
going to make your life miserable." Come
on.
That's no recipe for success.
>> So, it's an angry young man.
>> Yeah. You just have to show people
respect. It really is that simple.
>> You know, when I my first job out of
college was I did radio sales and my
mentor sat me down and he gave me Dale
Carnegie's How to Win Friends and
Influence People, shake them in the
hands, look them in the eye,
ask them about their family. So, I would
think at CIA, is that not taught?
>> No.
And it should be the first thing that's
taught.
And it's not. It's ignored. You know,
another thing too, is they never tell
you in training,
"You don't want to be the heavy."
You know, we've been doing this for 75
years. We've learned that it's not good
to be the heavy. They never train you in
that way.
They They train you in something called
the asset acquisition cycle, spot,
assess, develop, recruit.
You go into the the the pretend
diplomatic cocktail party
and
you go up to a guy, "Hi, how are you?
I'm John from the American Embassy.
Where are you from?" "Oh, I'm from the
Polish Embassy." Okay, I'm not
interested in you because Poland's in
NATO, it's in the European Union. We
don't spy on Poland. We don't need to.
So, nice meeting you and I'm going to go
on to the next guy.
And the next guy is from, you know,
Iran. Okay, I'm going to be interested
in this guy.
Or I'm going to be interested in the guy
in the um
you know, the
let's say, I'll make something up,
Syrian Defense Ministry or the Russian
Foreign Ministry or whatever,
but they don't teach you be nice, be
friendly, cultivate the relationship.
You either have that in you or you
don't. Now,
sometimes you there are guys that need
to use a heavy hand. Those are the guys
in what's euphemistically called the
special activities division.
Uh but they're not
they're not going to diplomatic cocktail
parties to find their targets.
They get their targets from the White
House kill list meeting on Tuesday
mornings.
They're not doing what I was doing.
But I never ever ever found that being
the heavy was the way to go. Never.
>> Which foreign intelligence service is
the best at cultivating friendships and
relationships?
>> Friendships and relationships?
>> You know, that
that I would think the Iranians are
probably pretty good at it.
>> The Iranians are terrible at it.
>> Really?
>> Absolutely terrible.
>> is so
>> They are absolutely
>> They can't.
>> terrible. No.
>> Who would Who would you say that would
be
>> on who the target is. The Israelis are
very very good at
developing people who would be their
natural supporters anyway.
Um
we're good at it.
>> Okay.
>> The Brits are good at it.
Um
>> Russians no good?
>> The Russians are better off at using
their own people as sleeper agents.
Or throwing money at people who have
very significant um
problems.
If they identify you as somebody who's
got a gambling addiction or an alcohol
problem or a drug problem.
Um or somebody who's been passed over
for promotion too many times. Sure,
they'll they'll target you, but that
relationship is going to be strictly
based on
on money.
Um these other services, the Cubans. The
Cubans don't have money to pay sources.
They do it all out of a sense of uh
ideology and patriotism.
>> Did you ever feel Can you feel it when
you're being recruited?
When someone's trying to develop you,
did you feel that? Did you understand
that? Did anyone try to recruit you and
you didn't even know until later?
>> No.
When I was in the CIA application
process, I was invited to a
to a party.
I was in grad school.
And my grad school advisor had recruited
me into the CIA, but I still had to go
through the security process. So, I'm in
that process and I'm invited to a dinner
party.
And the Hungarian, this is during
communism, the Hungarian third secretary
for education affairs.
It's just a made-up cover job.
Um
even I knew that at 23.
>> There's no travel budget for that guy if
he even exists.
>> This guy
was on me like white on rice.
He just would not leave me alone.
And
I got to thinking about it. Like, I
wonder if this guy's an intelligence
officer.
And so, since I was already in the
application process,
I called the recruiter and I said, "I
had this odd encounter a couple of
nights ago."
And I gave him the the guy the guy gave
him his business card. So, I said, "This
is his name. This is his position. This
is his his telephone number." And then,
once I got hired by the agency, I was
talking to the security officer that
cleared me and he said, "You know, that
was an intelligence officer."
He was young and inexperienced and a
little too overeager, but you did the
right thing reporting it.
And the second time it happened, I was a
senior officer.
And um
I was in Islamabad and my chief says, um
"I want you to meet with the French
head of counterterrorism here." And I
said, "Okay." So, I called the guy.
And uh I said, "Let's get together for
lunch." He says, "Okay, let's meet on
the corner of this street and that
street."
And I'm like, "What?"
That's a residential area.
Now, maybe there's a little cafe that I
don't know about. So, I said, "Okay."
So, I'm standing on this corner
waiting for the guy.
And it's a residential area. There's no
cafe or anything. And he screeches
around the corner, leans over, opens the
door, and says, "Jump in."
And I said, "You set me up for a car
pickup?"
A car pickup is when you're meeting with
a sensitive source,
you pull around a corner as quickly as
you can so that in case you're being
followed, the guy can jump in your car
without the chase car seeing that you've
picked somebody up, and then you kind of
cut through alleys and stuff.
And I said, "I am not your asset."
So, I wouldn't get in the car.
And I said, "I'll meet you at the Pearl
Hotel. We're going to have coffee in the
coffee shop. I'm not doing a car pickup
meeting with you. How dare you try to
recruit me?"
And then there was one other time I've
talked about on
on podcast, my very first briefing as a
CIA officer. I'd been on the job 6
weeks.
And my boss says to me,
"Listen, today you're going to do your
very first liaison briefing. This is a
joint briefing of Israeli Mossad and
Shin Bet."
And it was like eight of us, eight
analysts with these two Israeli
intelligence officers.
He said, "We don't allow the Israelis
into the building.
We used to, but every time they'd come,
they would bring gifts, and the gifts
are completely packed with listening
devices and batteries.
Like, we're not going to x-ray them.
And then we had to keep telling them,
"Guys, you can't keep coming here and
trying to bug our conference rooms every
time you come."
So, finally the director said, "Israelis
are not permitted in the building
anymore."
So, we rented a a space, a safe house,
and we would meet with the Israelis in
the safe house.
So, this is my very first briefing, and
they told me you're going to go last
since you're the most junior. So, the
the chief analyst starts first, then the
Iraq political, then the Iraq military,
then the Iraq economic, then the Iraq
oil, and then they finally came to me.
So,
this woman from Mossad, man from Shin
Bet, and they're writing down every
word. Now, I was overt at the time.
So, I used my true name, which was what
I was supposed to do.
And I said, "I'm John Kiriakou, and I'm
going to brief you today on Saddam
Hussein's psychological state."
And the Shin Bet guy has his glasses
down like this, and he says,
"Spell your name?"
So, I spell it, and he goes,
"You are
Jewish?"
And I said, "I am not recruitable.
Don't even think about trying to recruit
me."
I was furious. I could barely get
through the briefing. So, I go back to
the office, and my boss said, "How did
it go?" I said,
"This SOB tried to recruit me right in
front of everybody else."
And he laughed, and he said, "The
Israelis do that to every one of us.
Every single one of us.
Because they figure if they pitch a
thousand guys,
one's going to say yes eventually."
>> Glengarry Glen Ross, always be closing.
>> Mhm.
>> Right? And even coffee's for closers.
>> That's right.
>> That's really, you know, they they seem
from the outside so ham-fisted and
aggressive that it wouldn't work, but it
seems to be working just fine.
>> Look at Jonathan Pollard.
>> They're running the table on us.
>> They are.
>> It was announced yesterday, I guess,
that they've been elevated to the
highest risk for spying on us.
>> Yes. Well, and and they had been at the
highest previously.
One of the very first briefings you get
when you join the CIA is a
counterintelligence briefing
by the uh
the director of security. Very first day
at the CIA. So, you're in the bubble,
which is the auditorium, and the first
person out is the director of the CIA.
Welcome to the CIA. We're so happy to
have you. And then HR comes out and says
this is the health insurance and this is
the life insurance, whatever.
Chief of security comes out and gives
you some basic ground rules.
Don't ever go to the steakhouse down the
street. Ever.
Because the KGB thinks we all eat there
and so the KGB is at every table waiting
for a CIA person to walk in and start
talking about work. Right? So I've never
been there.
I've been in Washington 44 years. I've
never been to that steakhouse.
It's all KGB.
>> What steakhouse is this again?
>> It It's changed names a couple times.
It's TJ something now. One of the
>> I'm going. I'm bringing my friends and
we're going to pretend to be the CIA and
we're going to spill secrets.
>> TJ Gilbert's.
>> As loud as we can.
>> It's called TJ Gilbert's.
>> All right.
>> So um
another thing that he said was um
Let's see. It was TJ Gilbert's. Oh, he
said uh
the highest tier
for counterintelligence is critical
threat for counterintelligence. These
are the countries that spy on us the
most aggressively.
At the time it was the Soviet Union, now
Russia,
China,
Cuba, North Korea, Iran,
and Israel.
With France just one little step below.
Um
They're so incredibly aggressive. He
said, "For example,
at the Israeli embassy in Washington,
there are two declared intelligence
officers. One Mossad, one Shin Bet. I
met them 6 weeks later."
He said, "But the FBI has been able to
identify 187 and 87 undeclared Israeli
intelligence officers spread all across
America, mostly in American defense
contractors stealing our defense
secrets."
Why?
We give the Israelis 98% of what we
have.
They want that last 2%.
>> 98%?
>> Well, and now in the National Defense
Authorization Act of 2027, which passed
the House a couple of days ago,
we're integrating
our military technologies. So, Israelis
will be sitting next to us at the
Pentagon.
>> How can this happen the same week that
we elevate them to the greatest risk?
>> Yeah. You tell You tell me.
Exactly. Well, let me add Let me add one
other thing.
Uh
Jonathan Pollard, famous traitor,
uh was was spying He was a naval
intelligence officer.
Uh he was spying for the Israelis.
Jewish-American
giving the Israelis uh information on
Soviet military movements.
No big deal, right? I mean, in the
greater scheme of things.
Until you realize that the Israelis were
then giving that same top-secret
information to the KGB
in exchange for plane loads of Russian
Jews
to allow them to emigrate to Israel.
So, it caused
what
the Pentagon what Secretary of Defense
uh
um Caspar Weinberger at the time called
grave
um grave damage to the national
security. It's the highest level of
damage.
So,
Pollard
does every single day of his 30-year
sentence
for espionage. Every single day he
didn't get one single day off for a good
behavior or halfway house or anything.
Sheldon Adelson,
now the late Sheldon Adelson, sends his
private jet to pick up
Pollard at prison,
fly him to Tel Aviv.
When he gets off the plane, he's met
Excuse me.
He's met by Benjamin Netanyahu.
Pollard gets off the plane and kisses
the ground.
He's bestowed with
Israeli citizenship.
And in a speech at the airport
urges American Jews to take up arms
against the United States.
And then what happens? He's welcomed
into the American Embassy by Ambassador
Huckabee
for a meeting like some kind of
conquering hero.
Where are our priorities here?
Either the Israelis are a
counterintelligence threat
or they're not.
Well, they've proven that they are.
So,
are we serving the American people
or are we serving Israeli national
interests, national security interests?
>> Well, according to
>> do both.
>> According to Joe Kent
who seemed to be in a pretty good
position
>> Mhm.
>> to have visibility on all this. I'm
really eager to hear what Tulsi Gabbard
has to say in the coming months.
>> Mhm.
>> Um it seems to be we're serving the
interests of Israel.
>> Israeli Prime Ministers come to the
United States all the time.
Sometimes multiple times a year.
>> I've met Netanyahu in my life like 10
times being in the conservative
movement. Sat next to him at breakfasts
and lunches. He's worked very hard at
cultivating his relationships here in
the United States.
>> Over the course of a lifetime.
>> Yeah, since the '90s. I probably first
met him in the late '90s at a Christian
Coalition dinner. I got to sit at the
same table.
>> Uh I'm going to blow my own horn for a
second.
>> Okay.
>> When I was going through the application
process for the CIA, this was 19
eight or nine.
Uh 89. I had to go in for interviews.
And I'm at the very end of the process.
So, they give me a file folder about
that thick and it's full of newspaper
clippings. Every one of them is about
Benjamin Netanyahu. He was the Israeli
Ambassador to the United Nations at the
time. And they said, "Take 2 hours,
review all of these articles,
and then write a one-page
um
psychological analysis of Benjamin
Netanyahu."
So, I did.
And I said that
my conclusion was that he would probably
become Prime Minister of Israel one day.
And
and he did.
>> was this?
>> 1989.
He was ambassador to the UN, then he
became ambassador to the US, then he was
like defense minister, then foreign
minister, and then he became Prime
Minister. Now, he's the longest-serving
Prime Minister in Israeli history. But
um
W- Why was I telling you that? Oh,
Netanyahu
>> him. And and
was that by sheer force of his will and
ambition?
>> Absolutely, yes.
He's brilliant. He's dangerous,
but he's brilliant and a real political
player. He just runs rings around every
other Israeli uh political figure.
So,
from
the 1980s, when Ronald Reagan was was
president,
every Israeli Prime Minister, but even
before Netanyahu,
when they would come to the White House,
they would say, "Please bomb Iran.
Please bomb Iran. Please bomb Iran."
And every single president said, "I'm
not going to bomb Iran."
Until this one.
But even Barack Obama said a couple of
weeks ago
that Netanyahu asked him to bomb Iran.
And he said, "We're not going to bomb
Iran for you." And he said, "If you
don't bomb Iran, we're going to use
nuclear weapons."
And Obama said, "Go ahead.
Go ahead. Do it. Use nuclear weapons."
And he backed off because it was a
bluff.
>> Yeah.
>> But he made the same bluff with Donald
Trump, and Trump believed it.
>> Mhm.
Yeah, I don't know if it's wishful
thinking or not, but I do feel that
everything Trump is doing is going
against everything he said he would
never do and would be really stupid. And
so, I think that there must be something
that he thinks is for the greater good
for him to do something that is so
obviously really stupid.
>> I think that's right. I think Trump
really believed that he was doing the
right thing. I think that he believed
that over the long term he would be
saving lives and he would be supporting
long-term American foreign policy goals
by doing this. And I think now he
realizes he's been duped.
>> I think so, too. There seems to be a a
sudden
a sudden shift. I want to talk about the
psychology of Netanyahu. You seem to be
that's how you were recruited. And and
and I want to go back to how you were
you were recruited still when you were
in grad school.
>> Yeah, I was in grad school.
>> Which means they identified your
professor as a recruiter, they
identified you as a likely recruit.
>> Mhm.
>> Was that Hungary or Russia through
Hungary? Was Hungary that sophisticated?
>> Yeah.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah, the Hungarians, the Romanians, the
Bulgarians, they were very aggressive.
>> That's pretty good that they identified
him, identified you as a likely recruit,
and thought to recruit you while you
were still in the process.
>> Yeah.
Yeah.
>> But I want to go back to that.
>> I want to go back to Netanyahu because
understanding the psychology of
leadership is they saw a gift your
professor saw you had that gift.
>> was the name of the class.
>> The psychology of leadership.
>> Netanyahu reminds me of Michael
Corleone.
He lost his brother.
>> Mhm.
>> He's really obsessed. And I really do
understand the obsession of that
generation, especially of Jews, to for
their security.
So, he seems like someone who wanted
nothing but to keep his family safe.
>> Mhm.
>> And he's doing nothing but destroying
his family.
>> Plus, he had he has what appears to be a
very long-term
view of these issues. But I think the
truth is
that while he may have a long-term goal
his short-term actions
are wrecking
the region, the whole region, to the
point where it's it's untenable
over the long term.
>> Is he Does he buy into this Messianic
religious
>> Absolutely.
>> just weaponizing it for his purposes.
>> Absolutely. They laugh at American
evangelicals. They laugh at them.
>> They've tricked them, duped them into
blindly supporting Israel.
You know, I I have a friend who's an
evangelical, a close friend, and he's an
anti-Netanyahu evangelical. And he says,
"You know, the problem with these
evangelicals, well, let me let's back
up.
Evangelicals believe that Jesus can't
come back until all the Jews have moved
to Israel, have returned to Israel,
right? And
and he said, "Here's what the disconnect
is.
Evangelicals think that they can force
the hand of God.
That their actions, oh, if we charter
enough planes and put enough Jews on
them, Jesus will come back. And then
Jesus is going to come back when Jesus
is ready to come back.
Not cuz you guys have
chartered all the planes.
Right? It's ridiculous.
>> It's ridiculous.
>> And and the Israelis know that these
fools have a lot of money
and they're willing to do whatever the
Israeli government wants them to do.
And so they take advantage of it.
You and I have had conversations in the
past that I think bear repeating here.
Where
we can't understand why so many people
who
proudly describe themselves as
Christians
actively work against the Middle East's
Christians.
We're talking about these the original
>> The descendants of the Jews that
accepted Jesus. The descendants of the
people who were in the upper room.
>> Exactly.
What about them? I'm still angry about
the bombing of St. Porphyrios' Church in
Gaza.
>> October 18th.
>> Mhm. I'm still angry about that. The
oldest
continuously operating church in the
world.
And 24 women and children took refuge
there, and the Israelis blew it up.
>> You know what else they blew up? We sent
in a a film crew into Tehran to document
the oldest Jewish extant Jewish
community in the world. The oldest
continuous synagogue in the world.
Uh the United States and Israel
flattened a synagogue 11 days after we
shot our documentary about 2 months ago.
It's gone. Wiped from the face of the
earth today today today
um
a Palestinian child was shot in the West
Bank, a baby, an infant. Yesterday
Taybeh was set on fire, the only 100%
Christian village in the West Bank. And
in the past week, four Palestinian
students, female students, were
kidnapped by the IDF, one a Christian,
one an American citizen, one on the
national football team.
And the world is
>> silent.
How about uh Shireen Abu Akleh?
Shireen Abu Akleh, the most important,
most highly respected journalist at Al
Jazeera.
An American citizen.
A Greek Orthodox Christian.
She's in the West Bank with a
bulletproof vest that says press and a
Kevlar helmet that says press.
She's standing with a cameraman behind a
tree cuz she doesn't want to get in the
way of anybody.
And as soon as she steps out from behind
the tree, an Israeli sniper shoots her
in the face
and kills her instantly.
As if that wasn't bad enough,
the IDF goes into the hospital where her
body is being carried out in a coffin.
They beat the pallbearers
to the point where they drop the coffin
and then they shoot rubber bullets and
smoke grenades into the Greek Orthodox
church while her funeral service is
taking place. And not a single word from
the American government. Not a word.
>> evangelical Christian leaders or
Catholic leaders.
>> I want to know where is Ted Cruz and
Lindsey Graham and Mike Huckabee when
these things happen.
>> No, and people will say, you know, in in
December when Gaza made it to the front
pages for about an hour and a half,
um all of a sudden on cue all the
evangelical Christian human rights
groups, all Catholic leaders, even uh
Catholic Bishop Robert Barron,
"What about Nigeria? What about
Nigeria?" To this day Bishop Barron has
never mentioned Gaza or the West Bank or
Lebanon. "What about Nigeria?" That
lasted for about a week. As if So
they'll say, well, you what about
what you know, what about Boko Haram? My
organization guards churches in Nigeria
and the only synagogue. We provide
security for this. So I understand we
lost an employee last year to Islamist
extremism in in Nigeria. I'm not naive
to this, but we lost two employees in
Gaza that were killed when our baby
formula warehouse was bombed. But
they'll say, well, you know, what about
Boko Haram? Like you want to compare a
nation state to a No, no, what other
nation state behaves the way the state
does to its minorities?
>> None that I can think of. You know, I I
used to I I used to teach
Don't judge me.
I used to teach at Liberty University.
The the largest evangelical university
in the world.
They called me right after I blew the
whistle on the torture program.
It was
It was Jerry Falwell Jr. that called me.
Even my wife said to me one time, we got
a Christmas card from Jerry Falwell Jr.
And she says, do you know Jerry Falwell
Jr.? And I said, yeah. She said, how?
I said, we send jokes to each other
every once in a while on email. Anyway,
[clears throat]
so
they offered me this job speaking in
lecturing at the Jesse Helms School of
Government.
And I said, are you sure you want me? We
probably disagree on 99% of the issues.
And Jerry says,
we want you because torture is not
Christian.
And I said, you know what? I'll take the
job.
And
I loved every second that I was down
there. We disagreed on a lot of stuff,
but I loved it.
So
we had this debate a lot
about the role of evangelical Christians
in the Middle East. And I could never
understand why in the world
they wouldn't stand up
for the original Christians.
They didn't even want to talk about it.
And it just kind of fell by the wayside.
And here we are all these years later
and they're still not talking about it.
They're still not interested.
>> You know, I had a relationship with him
because he our first my first film Bella
he got way behind. He leaned into it so
much. Was a big part of our success. Was
very kind. I know he got caught in a
kind of an embarrassing scandal.
>> Yeah.
>> But he seemed like a kind and this is my
frustration with a lot of my Christian
Zionist friends. They're better than me.
They're kind. They're thoughtful.
They're polite. They wake up every
morning and pray.
But then when you talk about this issue,
it's just like
And then you show them quotes from Ben
Gvir. You show them attacks on by
settlers on West Bank Christians.
>> And it's just
they cannot ex- they cannot see it. Now
is am I naive to think that the state of
Israel has been running aggressive
influence operations through our
religious communities, through Christian
radio, through Christian publishing? And
isn't the FBI and the DOJ's
responsibility to protect us from
foreign governments' influence
operations?
>> It is indeed. But the Israelis get a
break.
There are no
counter propaganda
counter intelligence operations against
the Israelis. The AIPAC doesn't even
have to register as a foreign as a
foreign agent.
Which is nuts to me. You know, if a few
years ago more than a few years ago,
I won a very small contract, very modest
contract.
I don't know, five, six, eight thousand
dollars, whatever it was, to write a
series of op-eds in support of um the
Abu Dhabi Chamber of Commerce, right? Do
business in Abu Dhabi. There are no
taxes. It's friendly business
environment, that kind of thing.
And I had to register as a foreign agent
because I was doing this on behalf of a
foreign state.
AIPAC is the biggest agent of any
foreign state in America. But they're
exempt from filing.
Why?
Why do they get special treatment?
I'll give you another example
of how
powerful AIPAC has become.
I'm sure you've read articles, you've
seen news reports about how there are
AIPAC
employees literally assigned to every
office on Capitol Hill. Every single
one. All 535.
And they participate in meetings as if
they're staff members.
They write legislation, which is nuts to
me, but they write legislation.
Um
Nobody else is like that. Well,
a Texas state senator called me a few
months ago
and said, "Hey, I followed your case. I
followed you on the, you know, the
speaking circuit and all this stuff." He
said,
"I want to
draft a resolution for John Kiriakou Day
in the state of Texas." I said, "Oh my
god, thank you so much." He said, "We do
this 140, 150 times a year. It's just
pro forma.
Everybody just votes yes and
everybody gets a certificate from the
governor with a shiny gold seal." I
said, "Ah, thank you. It's wonderful."
He calls me like 3 weeks later. He says,
"Listen, I'm sorry, but that John
Kiriakou Day, that's not going to
happen."
And I said, "Really? What happened?" And
he says, "AIPAC objected."
I said, "AIPAC?"
>> I want this for the Gen Z to hear this.
This is important.
AIPAC in Texas state legislature vetoed
John Kiriakou Day. [laughter]
>> I was like, "Are you kidding me?" And he
said, "No, they're in all 50 state
legislatures."
I said, "I had no idea." He said,
"Actually now
they've gone lower and they're being
they're getting involved in mayoral
races, city council races, school board
races
because
>> They're building their bench.
>> That's exactly what it is.
You He the words right out of my mouth.
>> And then the problem is now I'm 55 years
old.
They built a relationship with me since
I was 18, 19, 20 years old. I feel a
debt.
>> Yes, exactly.
>> This is a debt I have to people who gave
me everything I have in my life.
>> You know, for a couple of years I was
the senior investigator on the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee.
Uh from 2009 to halfway through
2011, I think is what it was. And um I
had already worked on Capitol Hill. I'd
been on the house side, so now that was
as a junior staff member. Now I'm a
senior staff member on the Senate side.
And literally the first day
that we take office, John Kerry is the
chairman, so I'm working for Kerry.
These two guys just walk right into my
office. They don't knock on the door or
anything, just walk right in. And I look
up, I said, "May I help you?"
"Hi. Welcome to Capitol Hill."
I'm like, "Yeah, thank you. I I've been
on Capitol Hill before. May I help you?"
"We're from AIPAC." And I said, "Okay."
"We wanted to offer you uh an
all-expenses-paid trip to the Holy
Land."
I said, "No, thanks, guys. I can pay for
my own vacations."
"Oh, we'll take you to all the Christian
holy sites." I said, "No, thanks, guys.
I'm not interested." "Well, so far seven
of your colleagues are going." I said,
"Good for them. I'm not interested."
Finally, I had to tell them, "Just get
the hell out of my office."
>> And it just went downhill from there.
>> And these tours are Potemkin Village
tours.
>> That's exactly what they are. I'll tell
you another thing.
Just a year earlier in 2008,
um my mom called me. My my dad died in
2003, and my mom never quite got over
his death. And so she was depressed, and
she wanted to do something
to pass the time. So she called me, and
she said,
"NPR is giving a tour of Ireland. I I
going to go to Ireland." I said,
"Ireland?" I said, Mom, it's February.
You know what the weather's like in
Ireland? I said, I said, Father
>> NPR, that was their fun fundraising
event.
>> February 8th in Ireland.
>> NPR, come on. Okay.
>> So, I said I said, Father Ted's going to
take a group to to Israel. Why don't you
go to Israel with all the
all the church group?
And she said, oh, that's a good idea.
So, she and my sister went to Israel.
And [snorts]
my mom
uh God bless her, she was kind of an
innocent soul, right? She didn't know
anything about politics or international
affairs or anything. So, she gets back.
And I told her in advance, I said, take
pictures of literally everything. This
is the trip of a lifetime. Take pictures
of everything. She came back with
hundreds of pictures.
So,
their driver
for this little van that they had
driving them from site to site was a
Palestinian Christian, Catholic guy.
And um
she got back and I said, how was it? And
she said, did you have any idea how they
treat those Palestinians?
And I said, of course I do. She said,
it's scandalous. And I said, yeah.
And she said that
you know, you're driving around Israel
like, oh my god, it's first world, it's
incredible, it's high-rises and
everything is, you know, there's Cartier
over there and and you know, Saks Fifth
Avenue over here.
And then you cross into the Palestinian
areas. And she said, it's like going
into a prison.
There are literally walls with barbed
wire. And I said, yeah.
She said, to make matters worse
their driver
he's done these tours a thousand times.
So, he's not going to go into the, you
know, Church of the Nativity again or to
this place or to that place. He'll drive
you up to it and then he just sits
there. And he had one of these little
pulp fiction
dime store novels that he was reading.
So, they get stopped at an Israeli
checkpoint.
And the IDF comes onto
van and everybody had to hold up their
American passport. But then they
snatched the the driver's
novel out of his hand and the Israeli
soldier says
he opens the book, he says, "No picture
of Arafat on this page." and tears out
the page and throws it at him. "No
picture of Arafat on this page." and
throws it at him. And then he ends up
tearing up the whole book and throwing
it at him. And the guy just sat there
and took it because he had to sit there
and take it.
And she said the craziest thing was
that that was not the exception.
That kind of thing happened every time
they got stopped.
And I said, "That is life in modern-day
Israel."
>> Last week my team had a camera crew in
Taybeh for a Marian festival.
The IDF rolled in, drones, helicopters,
armored vehicles throwing stun grenades
at the Marian festival.
Um the day before we just happened to be
interviewing the owners of the Taybeh
brewery, the oldest brewery and
microbrewery in the Holy Land and the
only one maybe and now still in
operation.
We have footage of it cuz my one of my
guys hid the camera
>> Oh.
>> and kept the mics on.
>> Wow.
>> And and a an Israeli soldier with they
came in were abusing the owners,
refusing to allow a doctor to come check
on the mother, the grandmother.
And you can hear one of our recordings
in Hebrew but with an American accent
um the soldier says to
the woman, "I'm so sorry you're having
to go through this." Then the IDF
soldier's commander yells at him and
says, "We don't Get out of here. We
don't talk to those animals like that.
Don't show them any respect."
>> Mhm.
>> And so when you hear the stories
it's like a madras. You have to pity
these child soldiers, these radicalized
settlers, these radicalized guys in the
IDF because
they they're hate they have such hatred.
There's someone who's a prominent
conservative American leader who is big
in Hollywood and is a settler outside of
Bethlehem.
>> Oh my
>> Yeah, one of the owners of a major
Christian television network or movie
network. Um
>> Oh my god.
>> And he is a settler and I know him from
my film days. I actually like him quite
a bit. So, I'm in Bethlehem and I call
him and I say, "Hey, brother, will you
meet me in Bethlehem for coffee?" He's
like, "They're going to kill me.
They're going to kill me. It's so
dangerous. Get out of there. What are
you doing here?"
And I And I remember the first time I
went to the West Bank, I was nervous
because I hear all of my friends, they
go on these tours.
>> It tells them
>> them. They're like they were so brave
and then you're like, "It's safer than
my neighborhood." The people are so
kind. I don't see I expected to see boys
with green bandannas marching. Now, my
son, my 12-year-old wakes up every
morning, puts on camo,
gets his break barrel gun, puts on a
rucksack, and patrols the neighborhood
for ISIS. Every day, my 12-year-old. We
home school. This is how him and his
friends begin the day. That's the I see
that every day. You know, we're not
radical funama, but and I never saw a
kid play with a weapon. And I I said to
I never saw kids play army, play war. I
saw them riding bikes and jump roping
and kicking a soccer ball, playing
basketball. And I said, you know, in
America, we have this vision that your
kids were all out of bed with their
wooden
uh rifles and then they march in the
streets and they laugh. They go, "Why
would we play war?"
>> Yeah. Right, when they live it.
>> We live war. It's not a It's not
something we think is fun to play.
>> May I ask you a question?
>> Yeah.
>> One of the things that I've been grossly
disappointed um with
uh over the last, I'm going to say 15
years or so, is the uh the behavior of
the Arab Gulf states vis-à-vis the
Palestinians. Now, I get it. I lived
through the First Gulf War.
Um
For the For those of you who don't know
the background,
Yasser Arafat was the head of the
Palestine Liberation Organization at the
time. And
there were two members of the United
Nations Security Council at the time,
Cuba and Yemen, that we were a little
worried about. So, Saddam Hussein
invades Kuwait.
And uh the Bush administration
goes to the Security Council for use of
force. We tell the Cubans, we don't have
any sway over the Cubans. We tell the
Cubans and the Yemenis, you better vote
yes on use of force cuz we had the
Russians with us, the Chinese, the
British, the the French, all the
permanent members. We're going to
liberate Kuwait.
The right thing to do is to vote yes.
The Cubans and the Yemenis voted no.
But Yasser Arafat came out in support of
Saddam Hussein.
Well, there were
6 million Yemenis in Saudi Arabia as
guest workers. Literally every single
one of them was expelled.
Yemen has never recovered. In fact, it's
way worse now. It collapsed the
government.
Every Palestinian was thrown out of
Kuwait.
And not just Kuwait. We liberated Kuwait
a couple of months later. Every
Palestinian was thrown out, but they
were also thrown out of Bahrain,
Saudi Arabia, Qatar, Oman, and the
United Arab Emirates.
Well, they were the middle class, the
Palestinians. They were the
>> Most well-educated people in the
>> the engineers, the professors, the most
the the dentists and doctors and the
bankers, the entire middle class.
The Palestinians have never recovered
from that stupid decision to support
Saddam Hussein.
And so, here we are all these years
later. We're talking now 36 years ago
this happened. 36 years ago.
Is it still, do you think, because of
that decision
in August of 1990
that the Arab Gulf states
continue to have their backs turned to
the Palestinian people?
>> There's a real fear.
I I When I'm there, the only Gulf state
I'll go go anymore is Qatar.
>> Mhm.
>> I just get angry at how the migrant
workers are treated. I just I get so
angry. I'm from Hawaii. My parish is all
Filipino and I go there and I see it and
I get angry.
And so I just don't I don't go. And
cutter I see it I see how with dignity
the migrant workers are treated from my
experience.
Um you know the Israeli lobby will say
that they're they were kicked out
because they're such dirty awful they're
Amalek they're awful.
>> Just simply not true.
>> you know I wrote an article after my
first visit to the actually we were
evacuating wounded Christian women and
children from Gaza into Egypt. We would
bring them at the border. We would take
them to Cairo. We had a clandestine
studio because even Egyptian
Egypt didn't want us interviewing these
people.
And while I was interviewing them, I'm
running the operation to rescue them.
But I still had all these preconceived
notions. And as I'm interviewing them,
I realized I had been indoctrinated that
I had been such a bigot.
I had interviewed women who the IDF came
into their house, bombed their house,
smashed their statues of Mary, put on
their underwear. We have it on our
website vulnerablepeopleproject.com
cuz they put themselves on the internet
on the on social media in her underwear
prancing around smashing her statues of
Jesus. And then she would say
I just really feel sorry for these young
reservists who have been propagandized.
I feel so sorry for them. Then I
interviewed an elderly Muslim couple
that we had evacuated. And I was the
woman was telling me that she used to
use the tunnels to go to college to go
to grad school in Egypt. And I would say
in my mind I was like
a Palestinian man of this generation
would let his
And then you discover no they have a
they have a much higher level of second
of graduate education among their women
than Israel does. That they're well
educated.
And when I first went to the West Bank
I'm like okay Bet Sahour and Bethlehem I
feel great at but Ramallah is going to
be scary. And the more I roamed around,
I just feel at home.
When I call my wife from Iraq or from
the West Bank she's like we're not
moving there
>> [laughter]
>> cuz she But I don't feel at home in
Israel at all.
>> No.
>> It's It's an eerie feeling. It's an un
>> And we've all seen the videos of, you
know, nuns being attacked, and punched,
and spat on, and priests are being spat
on, and Yeah, what's that all about? And
we're supposed to leap to Israel's
defense?
Why? Why would we do that?
We're either We're either supporters of
human rights or we're not.
You can't pretend to be.
You know, I I was the human rights
officer
in both Kuwait and Bahrain. So, I had to
write the annual human rights report and
send it to Congress.
And
the ambassadors that I worked for,
career ambassadors, told me to pull no
punches.
Right? I remember going into I was in in
Bahrain, I went into the Minister of of
uh Interior's office. I said, "Your
Highness,
you cannot pick up a 15-year-old child
on the street, beat him to death,
because he marched in a pro-democracy
demonstration, and then call his parents
and say, "Come and pick up the body." I
have to report that to Congress. And
they may cut off your your military
sales.
And then we say to the Israelis, "Oh,
no, don't worry about it. Don't worry
about it. Everything's fine. Congress
isn't going to pay any attention."
What's up with that?
We're either going to be champions for
human rights or we're not. We can't just
pretend that we're champions for human
rights.
>> No, we I feel I want a unipolar world
with us at the top.
>> Yeah, sure.
>> up here competitors. But I think the
best way to do that is to work for the
shared interests of the community of
nations. And if we don't, we see BRICS.
We see nations are going to say, "We
need to figure out a different way,
because this way is not working for us."
>> Just wait till BRICS develops a unified
currency, then we're done.
>> And the only reason this is happening
is because we have demonstrated that
human rights is a tactic.
>> Mhm.
That's right.
>> It's just uh we you we speak about human
right. We all believed it in this 80s
and 90s. I believed in all of this.
>> Mhm.
>> And maybe it's something we used to
believe in and we we lost we lost faith
in.
>> You know what frustrates I got this
tattoo in Bethlehem.
>> I was admiring it.
>> It's Ecclesiastes 4:1.
And uh it's King Solomon said I looked
all over the world and all I see is
oppression. And on the side of the
oppressor is power. And on the side of
the oppressed there's no one. I got this
tattoo so when I shake powerful people's
hands, which I have the privilege of
doing often, they'll ask me what it is
then I'll I'll say it. I'll say can I
ask you a question?
Um do you stand with the Palestinians
against oppression?
>> And they never say yes, do they?
>> King Solomon telling the truth?
>> Mhm.
>> And they never say anything. Looks like
I slapped them. But but the truth is as
Christians
this is no longer true. And I found this
in my work around the world. And and
maybe I want to get back to you at it's
CIA cuz I think this is an example of
this.
You can look all over the world now and
see oppression.
>> Mhm.
>> And on the side of the oppressor is
power.
>> Mhm.
>> But on the side of the oppressed
everywhere, whether it's the Dalit in
India, the Uyghur in Chinese occupied
East Turkestan, the Yazidis in Iraq,
wherever I go and I see the oppressed
who do I find with them? The body of
Christ. I find Christians.
>> Mhm.
>> So now let's go back to you. You're at
CIA.
And you have this moral dilemma.
How much did your faith impact your
decision?
>> Oh.
100%.
You know, just to give you some
background, too.
Um
we never missed a Sunday growing up.
And it it wasn't just
it wasn't just that that our faith was
important to us. It was that the church
was the center of our culture. You know?
Our our friends were all Orthodox. I
grew up in a very heavily Catholic town.
I I barely even knew any Protestants.
Everybody that I knew and was friendly
with was
either Catholic or Orthodox, mostly
Catholic.
And um
it was very ethnic town that I grew up
in New Castle, Pennsylvania.
And so
the church was the center of our
of our, you know,
lives, our social circle, everything.
When I went to the CIA
I immediately gravitated toward this
group of
Greek-Americans.
And you know, at first I just thought,
"Oh, that's nice. All the Greeks get
together and have lunch once a month."
I didn't even realize as a junior
officer it was all these senior officers
looking out for me.
>> Mhm.
>> Right?
>> about you.
>> Yeah. And I didn't even It didn't even
register with me. Like these are these
people are mentoring me as I'm going
through my career.
And they're saying,
"You might not want to take that job.
You might want to think about taking
this job."
Or
you know,
"I'm volunteering to go to Afghanistan."
"No, no. You don't want to go to
Afghanistan.
You want to go to Pakistan.
There's more substantive work. They're
just killing people in Afghanistan. You
don't want to do that."
Things like that.
So
so it it became
a consistent theme through the course of
my career. And
I left my wallet downstairs. In my
wallet I keep a a photograph of a very
important 20th century saint, Saint
Nectarios of Aegina. He's also Saint
Nectarios of Pentapolis.
Um this was a guy
this was a guy that I have
I don't know why identified with more
closely than any other saint.
He's a 20th century saint. We don't We
don't make very many new saints in the
Orthodox Church. The Russians sanctify
everybody. They got 100,000 new saints
all the time.
But not us.
So,
Nectarios was the was the bishop of
Pentapolis, which is in Alexandria,
Egypt.
And he was a young bishop and very, very
popular because
he so identified with the poor. You
know, there are stories about him giving
away his shoes to homeless people
because he said, "Oh, I can always find
another pair of shoes somewhere."
Or going hungry so that others
had something to eat. Or
heading a heading a a seminary in Athens
later in his life
and when the the janitor got sick and
could no longer work, he cleaned the
toilets so that the janitor didn't lose
his job because he had children at home.
>> Oh, that's beautiful.
>> The bishop.
Um but anyway, he was driven out of
Pentapolis because older priests were
jealous of the fact that that his career
was moving so quickly and they began
spreading rumors that he was having um
affairs with parishioners. It was a
terrible, damnable lie.
And so, he was fired
and sent back to Greece. Well, back then
in those days, we're talking about like
the 1860s
or 1870s.
It wasn't like it is now where priests
are, you know, government employees and
they have nice pensions and the church
owns half the property in the country.
If it wasn't for the generosity of your
parishioners, you starved.
And so,
he practically starved.
And then,
he received permission to build
a monastery, not a monastery, a convent
on the island of Aegina
and um
and began attracting nuns to go and
study and lived out the rest of his life
there.
Well,
he never stopped
trying to
reclaim his reputation.
But, from the very beginning, he forgave
everybody for what they did to him.
This idea
>> identified with him as a boy.
>> As a boy.
>> This was the grace of God.
>> In fact,
>> preparing you.
>> I I'll tell you one funny thing that
I've never said before.
When I first got assigned to Athens,
I'm working very closely with the Greek
intelligence service. And they said,
"Listen, we need to do an operation on
the island of Aegina."
And um
I said, "Yeah, great. Let's do it."
So, we had to take a hydrofoil over to
the island. It's very close to Athens.
Back then, it was like 40 minutes.
>> wait till they make your movie because
you on a hydrofoil to Aegina, this is
Hollywood.
>> It's awesome, yeah. So, we get there
and we weren't sure if the sea was going
to be choppy that day or smooth. So, we
said, "Let's go like 6 hours early so in
case it's choppy and we're delayed, we
can still get there in time to do the
operation."
So, we we get there
and it's smooth as as oil.
The Greeks say uh ithalassa san ladi.
The The sea was just as smooth as oil.
So, we get there 6 hours early.
And the head of surveillance
for the Greek intelligence service was a
very religious man.
And he says to me, "Have you ever been
to
Saint Nectarios's house?" I said, "Oh my
god, I forgot Nectarios is here on
Aegina. I would love to see the house."
So, we go to the house and the convent
and it's stunning. I took my son there
just a few months ago.
I never go to Greece without going to
the to the house.
And because we're like VIPs, right?
>> Yeah.
>> They let me sit on his bed.
And we went into his study and it's like
pictures of his parents from the 1840s
and
it was incredible.
So, immediately next to the house,
attached to the house, is a little
chapel and then next to the chapel is
his tomb.
Most of his relics have been dispersed,
but
part of him is still in the in the tomb.
And so,
I wanted to light a candle and say a
prayer and everybody's putting in 100
drachmas, right? Little 100 drachma
coin, which at the time was about a
quarter.
I didn't have any change.
So, I reached into my wallet
and the smallest
the smallest thing I had was a 5,000,
which was 20 bucks, 20 whatever,
whatever 24 bucks.
And I thought, "Ah, it's for the
convent." So, I put in the 5,000. The
head of surveillance had saw me put in
the 5,000 and I crossed myself and I lit
my candle and I said my prayer.
We later learned that he told everybody
in the intelligence service
to keep their hands off of me
and not to put surveillance on me
because I was a good Christian boy
and I meant them no harm.
>> That's unbelievable. All Going back to
your youth and then Yeah. That leads me
to my next question. Well, St.
Nectarios, did he find that redemption
in his lifetime?
>> Not really.
He died in 1920.
His [snorts] assistant lived until 1968
and if you're at all interested, there's
a there's a film on Amazon Prime called
Man of God
about his life that came out in 2020.
>> Seen it on there, suggested. I've never
watched it yet, so I'm going to watch
that for sure.
>> It's breathtaking.
Don't miss it. It's breathtaking.
And um
after
he he died he died from what we believe
was probably prostate cancer.
>> Okay.
>> So,
they realized he was near the end, and
so they put him on a donkey.
And the donkey carried him all the way
from the north side of the island all
the way to the port down the mountain,
and they put him on a boat, and they
sent him to Athens
to the Red Cross Hospital, which is
still there. It's right by the American
Embassy.
And
he died a couple days later in the
hospital. Well, there was a man in the
next bed
who was a farmer who had fallen off a
retaining wall, and he broke his back
and was paralyzed from the neck down.
And he was crying in the bed not because
he was paralyzed, but because
now he wouldn't be able to farm, and so
his wife and his children would starve.
And so,
the saint died in the next bed.
And when the nuns went in to wash his
body, they took his sweater off,
and they put it on the bed where the
paralyzed man was,
and he got up and walked.
>> Unbelievable.
>> That was the first of the I have chills.
It was the first of the major
of the major miracles that were
attributed to him.
As soon as these miracles began
happening, it was before he was even
buried.
The patriarch
of Alexandria
said, "Oh my god, I made a terrible
mistake."
Or we made a terrible mistake. And they
issued an apology
and said that they were wrong, he was
right.
But remember all those years.
>> I mean, we're talking 25, 30
>> Longer than that. 40?
>> 40 years.
>> 45 years? He forgave all of them. He He
still tried to to reclaim his
reputation, but he forgave all of them.
So, I'm reading this
the the the bishop of Pittsburgh was a
big fan of mine, the Greek Orthodox
bishop of Pittsburgh, and he would come
to prison to visit me. And he brought me
that book.
So, I read the book. I was like, this is
incredible. And then you couple that
with, you know, Nelson Mandela's ability
to forgive,
or
or Martin Luther King's ability to
forgive,
and Nick Daddyos' ability to forgive.
And I thought to myself, and who am I
that I should hold a grudge?
I mean, these men were wronged so much
worse than I was.
My God, if they can forgive, I certainly
can.
I'm friends now with a man named
Mohamedou Ould Slahi. Has anybody ever
heard of him? Mohamedou Ould Slahi?
This is a story.
Mohamedou Ould Slahi was a Mauritanian
medical student in Germany.
Not a political bone in his body.
And he's just living his best life,
going to med school. He's going to be a
doctor. He wants to go back to
Mauritania one day because it's poor and
he wants to help his people, etc., etc.
He's got a cousin
in Beirut.
Okay?
And the cousin's brother
is in Nouakchott, Mauritania, getting
married.
So, the cousin in Beirut calls Mohamedou
and says, "Hey, my brother's getting
married in Nouakchott. Are you going to
go to the wedding?"
And he says, "Yeah, I'm going to go to
the wedding. Are you going to go to the
wedding?" He said, "No, I can't I can't
leave Beirut." He couldn't leave Beirut
because he was in Al-Qaeda.
Mohamedou didn't know his cousin's in
Al-Qaeda.
CIA did.
And they said, "Hey, hey, hey, this
Al-Qaeda guy
in Beirut, he's calling this guy in
Germany, and the guy in Germany is going
to go to Nouakchott. We better call the
Mauritanians and snatch this guy.
So, Mohamedou flies back to Nouakchott,
goes to his cousin's wedding.
The cops come in. They say, "You.
Some people outside want to see you." We
put a bag on his head. We put him in a
Jeep, take him to the airport, and fly
him to Guantanamo.
He has no idea what is happening to him.
And we tortured him for 14 years.
And after 14 years, we said, "You know
what? This guy actually doesn't know
anything.
Maybe he really was just a medical
student."
And we let him go.
So, he got out.
>> Now, when he gets out, he's what? 36?
>> Oh, yeah. He's in his late 30s. He gets
out like the week that I get out of
prison.
And he immediately sets up a Twitter
account.
So, I'm on Twitter and I see Mohamedou
Ould Slahi. I remember when we snatched
him because there were a bunch of us
saying, "Wait a minute. Wait a minute.
We don't have any evidence against this
guy at all. Just because he had one
phone call
with with some random low-level Al-Qaeda
nobody in Beirut, we're going to snatch
the guy?"
I was always
overruled in those conversations. There
were a half a dozen people like that
that we ended up concluding, "Eh, it was
the wrong guy. What are you going to
do?"
So, I tweeted at him and I said,
"Mohamedou,
my my government will never apologize
for what it did to you. So, I apologize
for what it did to you."
He immediately DMs me.
And we've been friends ever since. I
wrote the forward to his book.
And he uh is the guest lecturer in every
one of my classes on the history of
terrorism. I I teach a grad school
course at the University of Salamanca in
Spain.
And um
I said to him, you know, you are like
Nelson Mandela and Martin Luther King
and a man you've probably never heard
of, St. Nectarios of Aegina. I said,
your ability to forgive transcends
anything that I've ever seen it
in anybody before.
And he said, what am I going to do?
I was going to be a doctor.
They took it away from me.
What am I just going to, you know, say,
oh, woe is me, I was supposed to be a
doctor?
He said, I have to just get on with my
life.
So, now of all things, he he lives in
the Netherlands.
He got married. He has two kids.
And he teaches
elementary school art.
And started a new life and is happy and
prosperous
because he was able to forgive.
And I have nothing but the deepest
admiration for something like that.
>> So, if you didn't have your faith
>> I would have nothing.
>> You'd be crushed.
>> Mhm.
>> So, I want to I want to go to this. So,
you it's it's hard to say this to you,
but you're really blessed because most
people there are a lot of people There's
a wonderful movie by Terrence Malick, A
Hidden Life, on Franz Jägerstätter.
Um Franz Jägerstätter was an Austrian
farmer who refused to say the loyalty
oath to Hitler. His bishop said, be
prudent, just say it. His priest said,
you're being ridiculous to say the
loyalty oath.
He said, I'm never going to say it. I'm
a Catholic man.
>> Mhm.
>> And they tortured him. The SS officer
was Catholic and sat him down and said,
do you think that the world's going to
celebrate you? They'll never know what
you do. This This is your, you know,
they'll never see what you're doing.
You're not a hero. No one will know. No
one will care. And that is actually
true.
Most people who make the decisions that
Franz Jägerstätter, your friend Mohamed,
you made,
they're not redeemed in this life.
>> No.
>> And the world never knows. So, this is
my question to you.
I want you to maybe tell us about the
darkest years of this experience.
And if
in during those darkest years, did you
resent the decision you made? Did you
regret the decision you made?
And if you knew
there would never be a redemption in
this life,
>> Uh
>> would it have been worth it?
>> That's the hardest question.
I can tell you
my
the two hardest times of my life.
The night of my arrest.
Never saw it coming. And it had been in
the works for years. I never ever
saw it coming.
And
the night I was arrested, they released
me.
And um
it was about 10:00 and my wife said,
"Come on, let's go to bed. It's been a
heck of a day."
And I said, "No, I'm going to stay up
and watch TV." I wasn't going to stay up
and watch TV. I was going to go down to
the garage and start the car and lay on
the back seat.
And just let it finish me.
And I think she suspected.
And she said, "No, come on upstairs."
And I said, "No, I'm not ready." She
said, "I'm insisting."
And so I did. I went upstairs.
And um and then my brother called me the
next day and he said,
"I know you can't see this.
But this is going to turn out to be the
best thing that ever happened to you."
And I said, "No, I can't see it.
I appreciate you saying it.
But no, this is the worst thing that
ever happened to me."
But then I decided to fight. And my my
ex-wife now,
she said,
she was trying to buck me up and she
said, "They have consistently
underestimated your resolve.
They've consistently underestimated your
toughness.
You have to fight them.
And then later she said,
"You have to keep talking about your
case
because eventually they're going to move
on to their next target, which they did.
It was Ed Snowden.
And she said, "If you keep talking,
your side of the story will become the
side of record."
>> Cuz they're not going to gaslight
forever.
>> That's right.
>> on all
>> They move on. They always move on.
And she was right.
>> Wise woman.
>> Yeah.
>> In that instance.
In that instance.
Uh
>> Yeah.
>> We'll give her that one, right? That was
>> admit to you that I am I am prohibited
by court order from discussing my
ex-wife in uh in detail.
>> Yeah.
>> But I will say that um
I will say that June 30th, 2018,
three plus years after I got out of
prison was the worst day of my life.
>> Okay.
>> Because
well, in Latin, the words in flagrante
delicto
>> Mhm.
>> mean something.
And um
>> I thought going to prison was bad.
>> This was way, way worse
than going to prison.
But you know, I remember laying there
in bed, quite literally laying in bed. I
suffered terribly from insomnia.
3:00 in the morning.
And against the advice of every
intelligence officer I've ever known, I
have an Alexa in my room, right? Cuz it
plays SiriusXM radio every morning, you
know.
>> Losing our
>> Yeah.
>> privacy is worth freedom.
>> Yeah, it's like, yeah, exactly. Like,
Alexa,
>> I think we all we all make that same
decision.
>> Yeah. So, I I'm laying there and I said,
"Alexa,
what percentage of marriages that begin
as affairs end in divorce?"
And she says,
"The percentage of marriages that begin
as affairs and end in divorce is 93%."
and I was like, oh, thank god.
Okay, so at least I've got that. I'm
going to hang on to that for a little
while. And then I'm laying there and I
have I have an iconostasis in my room,
right?
Icons that belonged to my great great
grandfather
from the early part of the 19th century
and icons that I've picked up around the
world, you know, over the years. I have
a a cross where somebody carved 1820
into the bottom of it. The crucifix.
And so I've got them all on a
on a shelf.
And I'm looking at them. And Saint
Nectarios is one and I have holy oil
from the monastery and
and holy water and stuff like that.
And I'm looking at the icons and I said,
am I really that bad of a guy
that I deserve this? Really?
What is it that you wanted me to do that
I haven't done?
Why do I deserve to be treated like
this?
I remember saying it out loud at 3:00 in
the morning.
And I remember being tempted to start
boycotting church,
which I had never done before. Like, ah,
I can't believe in this stuff anymore.
And then I thought, no,
that's what the devil wants me to do.
I'm going to stick it out. And I will
say, you know, there's one part of the
Greek Orthodox liturgy where the priest
says where the priest asks God to bless
those who love the beauty of thy house.
And I really do love the beauty of his
house.
You know, even after all these years,
decades of sitting in church, I still
look around at the iconography and I
just marvel at it.
I marvel at it.
And that got me through.
>> Did you reflect on the passion?
>> Oh my god.
>> my god, why have thou forsaken me?
>> All the time. Like, every time I start
feeling sorry for myself, I I to myself,
you should be ashamed feeling sorry for
yourself. After what all these other
people went through, after what Christ
went through himself,
and you feel sorry for yourself? Shame
on you.
And it snapped me out of it.
>> Yeah, I don't I can't wrap my mind
around how people in other faiths
grapple with the problem of the mystery
of human suffering.
>> Yes.
>> Because to me, Christianity has the
second person of the Trinity
exemplifying how one should bear
suffering.
>> Yeah.
>> And if we didn't have that, how do I
handle my child dying from leukemia, my
wife dying in a car accident?
>> Exactly.
>> How do you even wrap or being betrayed
by someone you love?
>> Yeah.
>> A um a friend of mine um
who is one of the greatest heroes I've
ever known. He saved more lives than
anyone, but he's constantly depressed
and feels like a failure because when
you do a job like his, you fail a lot,
and you don't remember your successes,
you remember your failures.
And while he was doing this all over the
world, his wife was running around
um where they were living. And um
I called him and I said, "Brother, I'm
really so sorry." And he said, "It's
very painful, but I'm just grateful
that I can I feel like now I'm really
getting empathy to how our Lord
suffered.
To be betrayed by people you love."
>> There it is right there.
>> And I thought, "Wow."
>> Pretty powerful. So, during those years,
those dark years, did you ever kick
yourself self and say, "Why did I do
this?"
>> No.
>> Never once.
>> I never did. And I can't even really
vocalize to you why I didn't. Well, like
I say, my ex-wife used to say
it was because
I'm so arrogant and so narcissistic
that I my brain won't allow me to think
that I did the wrong thing.
I'm like, "Okay."
All right.
And
so I just accept it. Maybe I am
arrogant. Maybe I am narcissistic,
But I know that I did the right thing. I
know it.
You and I were
have had this conversation in the past
where
the CIA culture is such that they want
you to believe that everything in life
is a shade of gray. Everything.
And that's just simply not true. Some
things are black and white. They're
right or wrong.
And in our guts, we all know what the
right thing to do is. All of us know.
The question then in modern culture is
is the right thing also the expedient
thing?
Right? If you do the wrong thing,
maybe you'll make a little bit more
money. Maybe you get that promotion.
Maybe something good happens to you in
the short term. But is that how you
really want to live your life?
You know? And that's not how I wanted to
live my life.
Another thing, too,
is money has never been important to me.
And I know that doesn't really make
logical sense to a lot of people. But
money was never really important to my
parents.
And because it wasn't important to them,
I grew up, you know, just as a kind of a
normal middle middle
maybe slightly lower middle
class existence. I never saw the ocean
till I was 16 years old. Never went on a
plane until I was 18 years old. We just
never
never did those kinds of things. We
never had the money to.
And so,
when I went into government service, God
knows you don't do it for the money.
They're not paying you anything. When I
When I got hired by the CIA, my annual
salary was $17,200.
You don't do it for the money.
And so, I thought, well, you know,
this is my lot in life. This is what I
was meant to do. It's not about making
money.
It's just about doing the right thing.
And I came to, you know, really believe
it.
>> And so, as you're going through all
this, you never had regret. Now, if I
would map your life out, and then I'm
going to I have Gen Z, you are the icon
to Gen Z. And there's no one I would
rather be
I am so grateful that they have found
you because there is a bewildering
mix of people they look up to.
And they all have like glimmers and
flashes of virtue. And then
but like you you are a man of that
presents himself and Gen Z recognizes
having integrity. And they it's just
like they drink they binge watch I I
told you one time my kids came to meet
with me. It was the day that my two old
my my 19-year-old and 18-year-old son
wanted to tell me they wanted to work
for me for a lot of their life like
serving the vulnerable people through
the vulnerable people project. And they
have said, "Yeah, Dad, there's this guy
you'd love. John Karakitsios." Like this
is early on and they were like they
could I said, "I don't know who you're
talking about." Then they started
describing I'm like, "Oh, John
Kiriakou?" They go, "Yeah." I'm like,
"Oh." I turned my phone around. Look who
just I was texting with. My kids' like
eyeballs popped out. And they said,
"Dad, do you know who he is?" I'm like,
"Yeah, he's my friend." He goes, "No,
no.
He's the biggest guy in the world." I'm
like, "Does he know that? I don't think
he knows that." And he's like he has to
know it. Like Gen Z has discovered him.
So, you know, Gen Z to me has been
totally forgotten.
The Pope Pope Leo just came out with
this beautiful encyclical that's being
criticized on AI.
>> the the Greek Orthodox Archbishop of
America
came out with an encyclical a couple of
days ago saying everybody needs to read
Pope Leo's encyclical because he's right
on.
>> I I think God for him. You know, it's a
fluke. I was in Rome for the
for the conclave. I was wearing a
Chicago White Sox hat.
And so, NBC Evening News and Chicago ABC
wanted to interview me.
And they'd ask me why he took the name
Pope Leo. And I said, "I think it's
because he recognizes that AI is a
threat to the working class the way the
Industrial Revolution is and we'll
probably get a an encyclical drawing on
Rerum Novarum." And that's exactly what
we got. And he has such a
thoughtfulness. AI, first of all, the
apps, pornography, has brutalized her
moral imagination, destroyed their
ability to experience authentic
awakening of the erotic. Um
they've got the OnlyFans, all of this.
And then now you have AI. So, you're
never going to get married, you're never
going to have kids, and guess what? Now
you're never going to have a job. And it
seems like the whole world is out to
lunch on this.
Um and so Gen Z is just like this,
anyone care about us? Is anyone thinking
about our future?
>> Yeah.
>> And then here you are. And they And they
discover you.
Can you explain a little bit why do you
think Gen Z has responded to you so
powerfully?
>> Well, the way it started is odd. It's
kind of a disconnect.
So, I gave an interview in January to uh
Steven Bartlett at Diary of a CEO,
the Diary of a CEO podcast.
>> So, it was just this January when it
took off.
>> happened. And I've been telling the same
stories for 19 years, and nobody paid
any attention.
So, I gave this interview, and it was
kind of the standard long-form
podcast interview, the same interview I
I've given to Tucker Carlson or or Joe
Rogan or a couple of others.
It was a little bit more philosophical.
And then I, you know,
got on the plane and went home.
A sophomore from the University of Texas
at Austin took that interview and cut it
into shorts,
sped up my voice, slowed down my voice,
shot lasers out of my eyes.
>> [laughter]
>> I'm loving this.
>> And it went completely crazy. Right
after that interview, I flew to Dubai.
I had a a contract there.
And my niece called me.
And she said, "Uncle John, you're
exploding on TikTok." I said, "Why?"
And she said, "I don't know, but it's
huge."
And I was like, "Uh, okay."
The next night at 2:30 in the morning, I
get a call from the Creative Artists
Agency, the biggest talent agency in the
world. They didn't know I was in Dubai,
so it was like afternoon for them.
And the guy says, "Tell me that you're
not represented."
And I said, "No, I'm not represented,
but what's going on?"
And he said, "You're just blowing up the
internet."
And they wanted to represent me. And I
said, "But why is this happening?"
And they were like, "We don't know,
but it's happening."
And I said, "Okay, sign me up."
That's the origin of it.
But the result has been
that
it seems that Gen Z trusts me
because I'm a truth-teller.
I don't have any personal agenda.
None.
I think that for the most part,
mainstream media lies to us every single
day.
And I think that
young people need to develop
the analytic skills necessary
to get to the bottom of issues on their
own cuz they're not going to get it from
Fox and CNN and MSNBC and the others.
They're not going to get it. People ask
me all the time,
"Where do you get your information?" My
answer is from literally everywhere.
It takes me hours every morning. I start
with The Washington Post, The New York
Times, The Wall Street Journal, The LA
Times, The BBC, The Times of London, AP,
Reuters, Al Jazeera, Al Monitor. I just
go down this list of 25 different
outlets.
Because you educate yourself enough
from every single point of view
so that you can make your own conclusion
based on the evidence that you're
seeing.
>> So, there's no email I can subscribe
that I haven't I haven't found it.
>> No, I haven't found it.
And I think that people have concluded
that
I'm telling the truth. The truth has
hurt me significantly
over the years, and I just continue to
tell the truth.
It really is as simple as that.
>> Could it be they also feel abused and
abandoned by the establishment?
>> that's a very important part of it.
>> and abandoned?
>> at look at affiliations with political
parties. They're at historic lows right
now.
I really believe that we're headed for
some sort of a watershed political event
in the country.
Um I'm not exactly sure what that's
going to look like yet, but think of it
this way. As recently as a century ago,
we had as many as six viable political
parties in this country.
We had cabinet members. Think of
Salmon P. Chase, the the Secretary of
the Treasury under Lincoln, or or
William Stanton, Secretary of War under
Lincoln.
They were each members of six different
political parties. If you had a problem
with a position that your party took,
you just quit.
>> And Lincoln didn't like any of them, I
think.
>> And team of rivals.
>> Yeah.
>> And you would just jump to a different
party.
So, how did we box ourselves into this
you know, this essentially uniparty,
this duopoly that's really a uniparty?
When a century ago, we had
we had a populist party, we had a
socialist party, we had you know, the
Free Soil Party and this party and that
party and the farmer
DFL, the Democratic Farmer Labor Party,
and
we had all these different parties that
were winning seats in Congress, that
were winning governorships.
Why have we relegated ourselves to two
sides of the same coin?
So, I think we're headed
we're headed towards something big. I'm
just old enough
to remember
1968 and 1969.
I remember sitting on my dad's lap.
He was watching the news, and the news
showed all these buildings on fire, and
I asked him why these buildings were on
fire.
And he said, "A very bad man killed
Martin Luther King and black people were
very upset." I still remember him saying
it like that.
And then a couple months later my mother
just crying all day because Robert
Kennedy had been shot and killed.
And then a friend of ours
uh a friend of my parents
um
lost his daughter
at Kent State. She was one of the the
five that was shot and killed. Yeah.
So, I remember this upheaval, these
riots in the streets, and the national
>> forming you. This was forming your moral
conscience.
>> Very much.
>> Losing a friend losing his daughter at
Kent State must have been a big part of
your identifying with the left.
>> Mhm.
It it very much was. Uh
Governor Rhodes Governor Rhodes was the
governor of Ohio that ordered the
National Guard just open fire on unarmed
students.
And in our house Governor Rhodes was the
devil.
You know?
Open fire on unarmed students for a
peaceful political protest. What is
this? North Korea?
You know?
And so yeah, that did inform my my
political views.
Um
so I don't know how we've gone from
the free thinking of '68 and '69 through
'74
which was the year of Watergate
to this thing where we pretend to have
these significant political differences
and we're just rearranging the deck
chairs on the Titanic.
>> That's that's what's happening. And Gen
Z knows it.
>> And they know it. They recognize
it.
>> and y'all are rearranging the deck
chairs."
>> it. Yes.
>> And Pope Leo recognizes it.
>> Leo recognizes
>> patriarch recognizes
>> Pope Leo has been
has had his intellect consistently
underestimated.
>> Yeah.
>> Mhm.
>> Well, he's from Chicago after he's a Sox
fan.
>> That's right.
>> So, there's that.
>> around the block.
>> Yeah.
>> So, I have some questions from Gen Z for
you.
>> Okay, great.
>> Okay, I had Gen Z-ers
uh the hope of the you know, they're
they're they're
I they're what gives me hope. Okay.
Is the CIA Oh, no, no, I want to ask
this question first.
Cuz this is a good question.
Okay.
Not saying that the moon landing was
faked or that the CIA was involved in
the killing of John F. Kennedy, but
as someone who worked inside the
intelligence community, do you think the
US government could keep a secret that
big, faking the moon landing,
assassinating a president, or hiding
aliens from us?
Could they if they wanted to hide that
those secrets from us?
>> [sighs]
>> I hate to be wishy-washy, but yes and
no.
Um
the moon landing wasn't faked, of
course. Um we've got the science to
prove it. But um
you know what? I'm going to answer that
with an anecdote that Bob Kennedy Jr.
told me.
And when he told me this, I said, "Bob,
you've you've got to write this down.
This
social scientists need to know this."
He said that
he said that on November 22nd
Did I say this already? November 22nd,
the day that his uncle was assassinated
in in Dallas, his mother went to
the junior high where he was attending
in McLean, Virginia
minutes after the assassination and
pulled him out of school.
And they drove back to the house. It was
called Hickory Hill, big mansion in
McLean, Virginia.
And he said he got out of the car and
his father was standing in the driveway
speaking with John McCone, who was the
director of the CIA. As background
both the Kennedys and the McCoans were
very devout Catholics.
And
Mrs. McCoan had died 6 months earlier
from breast cancer. The Kennedys were
very worried about Director McCoan. They
were worried that he was so distraught
by her death that he might harm himself.
And so, John McCoan had dinner with the
Kennedys seven nights a week. And after
dinner, he and Bob Kennedy would go
swimming together.
So, Bobby Jr. gets out of the car, walks
past his dad, and he hears his dad say
to Director McCoan, "Tell me your people
didn't do this."
And McCoan answered,
"I don't know who did it."
He did not say, "Of course my people
didn't do this. What in the world would
make you think the CIA would kill the
President of the United States?"
It's not what he said. He said, "I don't
know who did this."
So, did the CIA kill John Kennedy? Of
course not. Did elements of the CIA kill
John Kennedy?
I think that's something that we'll
never know the answer to, but I think
the circumstantial evidence is such that
we should be asking these questions
because it's entirely possible.
>> So, you know, as an outsider, when I
hear there are rogue elements within the
CIA, I'm saying to myself, "Oh, please
let that just be Hollywood fantasy."
>> No, there are there are rogue elements.
Especially, you know,
pre-1975, pre-Church-Pike Committees,
immediately post-9/11.
Yeah, I kind of make a a joke about this
uh this guy that I used to work with.
Friendliest guy in the world.
Rick.
I was working in the Counterterrorism
Center, and he would come in every day.
"Morning, fellas." We'd say, "Morning,
Rick."
"How was your weekend, fellas?" "Hey,
great, Rick. How was your weekend?"
"Yeah, great."
"Hey guys, you going to go to the agency
picnic?" "Yeah, Rick, we'll see you at
the picnic."
Finally, I said to the guy I was sitting
next to him, Frank. I said, "You know,
he's the nicest guy in the world and I
really don't know what he does here."
And Frank says, "He's the
head of the special activities
division."
So his job was every Tuesday morning
you get the kill list
which is what they called it. Every
Tuesday morning at the White House, CIA
people meet with the White House counsel
and their people
come up with a list of people to kill
that week.
Rick gets the list.
He sends his guys out. He goes out all
around the world. You kill the guy
that's on the list and you come back and
you get the next list the next Tuesday.
And I said, "Wow, that's
that's not good.
Right? I mean, none of these people have
been
charged with a crime.
If these are such bad people I mean,
this is the United States of America.
>> Yeah.
>> We have a constitution.
If these guys are so bad, charge them
with a crime.
You can't just decide you don't like
somebody's politics and go and blow
their brains out.
And as it turned out, some of them were
American citizens
who had never been charged with a crime.
Again, some things are right or wrong
and this is wrong.
After I left the CIA
Rick retired. He I left in '04, he
retired in like '06.
And in '07, Vanity Fair magazine wrote
an expose about him.
I couldn't believe what I read.
He had been a hit man for the Cali
Cartel.
And he struck up a friendship with
a dark figure
in my career who ended up becoming the
Deputy Director for Operations.
Because they were both working against
communist insurgents in Colombia.
Cuz the Cali Cartel
hated the communists and vice versa.
Well, the CIA hated the communists and
the enemy of of my enemy is my friend.
And so, the agency and the Cali Cartel
are working together to stamp out
communism as if that mattered.
And so, he says, "Hey, listen, if you
don't want to do Cartel hits anymore,
I'm I'm the CIA station chief down here.
Why don't you come and do hits for me?"
And that was it.
He was a hitman for the Cali Cartel.
That's not That's not cool.
>> No.
>> No. How How did that happen?
>> still doing this?
Are they still getting the kill lists?
>> Uh we don't know. They won't They won't
say. They won't tell us. The kill list
was outed in um The Atlantic Monthly
magazine.
The
um originator of the kill list was one
John Brennan.
And uh we don't know if
>> John Brennan's drone war killed hundreds
and hundreds and hundreds of children.
>> god. I have a friend, Daniel McHale.
Daniel just got out of prison himself.
He was a drone operator
from the US Air Force.
He's the one who blew the whistle on the
drone program. And he tells the most
chilling story.
He was operating a drone from a base in
Nevada.
His boss was at MacDill Air Force Base
in Florida.
So, they're both looking at the screen.
Daniel's operating the drone.
And he sees the target. The target's in
Afghanistan, right?
And Daniel says,
"I have eyes on the target." And his
boss in MacDill says, "Fire."
And Daniel says, "Wait a minute.
He's with two little kids."
And his boss says, "Those aren't kids.
Those are goats."
He said, "I'm looking at them. They're
not goats. They're children. They're
girls."
And his boss says, "Fire."
And he said, "I can't fire. They're
children."
>> It's an illegal order.
>> He says, "Fire or be court-marshaled."
And he fires.
And he kills a 12-year-old girl and a
9-year-old girl.
And he went home that night and he said
to his girlfriend, "I became a child
killer today."
How do you How do we live with
ourselves?
>> you recover from that?
>> You can't recover from that.
But this is what I what I mean when I
say
>> In Israel right now, they have a ramp
the suicide rate of IDF soldiers is
unprecedented.
>> It's got to be.
Because you can't all be monsters,
right?
>> Yeah.
>> Somebody's got to have a conscience.
>> Not Lindsey Graham.
>> No.
>> Not Randy Fine.
>> Lindsey Graham is perfectly happy
to kill your children and your children
and your children.
He doesn't care.
Yeah. And Fine, who wears an IDF uniform
onto the floor of the house like a
traitor.
>> Who did?
Oh, Fine. All right. Yeah, Congressman
Fine. He was shown a picture of a dead
Palestinian child.
>> Yeah.
>> And he said, "Oh, that's a lovely
picture. I'd like to see more of those."
And this isn't an international scandal,
but then Gen Z is watching this.
>> Normal people don't talk like that.
>> Yeah, it's not how normal people talk.
Ben Gvir, you listen to Ben Gvir talk?
>> His wife
Listen, the Israelis passed a law 2
weeks ago allowing for the death
penalty, but only for Palestinians.
Not for Jews.
And on the day that the Knesset passed
it into law, his wife baked him a cake
in the shape of a gallows.
These are not normal people.
This is not normal life.
We need to reclaim what's right.
>> You know, I think we're going to see a
political shift in this country like we
did after desegregation.
And ironically, it's going to be around
segregation.
You know, when you look at Israel, it is
a segregated apartheid state that makes
the Jim Crow South look like Utopia.
>> Very much so.
>> And I think it's hard for most Americans
to believe that, but you have settlers
attacking Christian villages with the
IDF pulling security. So, if you try to
protect yourself, protect your property,
you're shot right in the face or
arrested.
>> Yep.
And how many American citizens have been
killed in the West Bank in recent years?
>> this week.
>> Mhm.
And does the American government lift a
finger
>> No.
>> to do anything in the name of justice?
Nothing. Literally nothing.
>> It's frustrating. I can talk to you
about the West Bank and Gaza and
Lebanon. I mean, that's the nightmare,
too.
Okay, so here are some more Gen Z
questions.
Um
What do you know about Project Gateway
and using astral projection to spy on
the Soviets during the Cold War? This is
The Men Who Stare at Goats question. Is
that what this is? Okay.
>> So, Project Gateway was a part of what
was called MK Ultra.
MK Ultra was a very, very
broad scope operation that began in 1952
and ended in 1975 and included a lot of
different things.
ESP, astral projection, mind reading,
um
LSD and using LSD
to get people to
confess to their deepest, darkest
secrets. A whole bunch of different
stuff. It was a disaster.
And it ended up in the deaths of a lot
of people, a lot of innocent people.
So,
the way it started off was
the CIA recruited a source who was a
fake, a phony source, who said, "Hey,
the Russians are experimenting with
this, you know, ESP and astral
projection and mind reading and all this
stuff. We're behind the eight ball."
That wasn't true. The Russians were not
doing any such thing. The Chinese were,
but we didn't know that.
So, we said, "Oh my god, we have to we
have to get up to speed as fast as we
can."
And the CIA comes up with this program,
MK Ultra,
and they start just pouring resources
into it.
Beginning with LSD.
And
because
>> [laughter]
>> the CIA
>> [snorts]
>> often moves into the area of utter
lawlessness,
they start dosing their own employees
unwittingly.
You just just slip LSD into people's
coffee and
you know, their food, and just just see
what happens to them.
>> Well, I wonder what's going to happen to
Joe if I dose him with LSD.
>> Jacob's Ladder, if you've seen that
movie.
>> Joe's going to go to the roof and jump
off cuz he thinks he can fly.
And then you got to explain to his kids
why your dad went to work this morning
perfectly normal and then committed
suicide at lunchtime.
>> And this that happened.
>> Yeah, that happened. In fact, um there's
even been um
a documentary about it.
So,
that was one part of it.
They hired psychics and seers and
readers, and and it was all silliness
and nonsense. It never amounted to
anything. But then there were sub
operations of MK Ultra, like MK
Chickwit, for example.
Uh
>> [laughter]
>> where we broke into the lab in
Switzerland and stole the formula for
LSD, so we could make it better.
And then we just decided to
I'm not making this up. It's all It's
all out there on online. You can find
it. We decided to make San Francisco the
sort of the the headquarters of these
experiments.
And so So, hippy culture,
the Grateful Dead,
Fish, All All at the same time.
>> is the fruits
>> Yes.
>> of CIA.
>> It all came out of CIA. So, we decided
to recruit a whole contingent of
prostitutes.
And we set up a safe house.
So, we sent the prostitutes out to pick
up Johns, clients,
dose them with LSD, bring them back to
the safe house,
tie them down,
and get them to confess their deepest,
darkest secrets. And it just didn't
work.
They were just, you know, jabbering
incoherently and having flashbacks and
freak outs, and it just didn't work.
And then we decided,
"Well, let's uh
let's come up with a germ.
And we'll wait until a really foggy day
when the air is really heavy, and we'll
just shoot this germ into the air in San
Francisco, and just see if anybody gets
sick."
Cuz then we can do it in Moscow and
really screw them up. Right?
So, we come up with this germ that's
developed in a CIA lab.
We wait until an unusually foggy day,
and then just drive around the city with
these big pipes, just blowing the germ
into the into the atmosphere.
Two days later, 11 people came down with
this extraordinarily rare upper
respiratory infection
that had never been seen in San
Francisco before. And we were like,
"Hey, that worked.
We should we should do that in the
Moscow subway system
and see if we can really, you know,
screw them up."
Then there was another experiment where
they um
they decided to dose There's a small
village in France. I forgive me, I don't
remember
>> Was this a small
>> it was very, very small. It was tightly
held. Um it was a compartmented program.
So, we we went to this village in
France. It had one bakery that supplied
the entire village, and we dosed the
yeast. In the middle of the night, we
broke into the bakery and put LSD in the
yeast.
The baker comes to work in the morning.
He makes all the bread. He sells the
bread to everybody in the village.
Everybody in the village goes on an LSD
trip.
And then for decades we're like, "It
wasn't us. It wasn't us. It wasn't us."
And then in the '90s we're like, "Okay,
it was us."
And then finally
in 1975
the CIA had just gone too far, right?
We've we've just lost the Vietnam War
and everybody in the CIA is like
smuggling heroin back from Vietnam and
it's just a disaster. So, Senator Frank
Church, a Democrat of Idaho
convenes a a special committee known as
the Church Committee. Sen- uh
Congressman Otis Pike, a Democrat from
Long Island, convenes a
a parallel committee in the House side,
the Pike Committee. They morphed into
the Senate Select Committee on
Intelligence and the House Permanent
Select Committee on Intelligence.
And they started investigating the CIA
what what was then called the Family
Jewels.
Where they demanded
literally everything that the CIA had.
Well, the first thing that comes up is
MKUltra and associated assassination
programs.
The CIA wasn't supposed to be
assassinating people. In fact, it was
out there assassinating thousands of
people.
So, Congress put the brakes on that.
Senator Church specifically told the CIA
director
"Do not destroy the MKUltra documents."
Direct order.
He literally went from Capitol Hill back
to headquarters and said, "Destroy
everything."
And so everybody in the building is just
shredding documents.
They destroyed 85% of the MKUltra
documents. 15% survived. That's why we
have this little idea after all these
years of what it was, but we really
don't know what the overall program was
because it was all destroyed. Well,
the director was fined $500
for this egregious criminal act
of defying Congress. And the old-timers
used to talk about this when I when I
first got there.
>> what the IDF does for its soldiers when
they Oh, yeah. Yeah.
>> Uh by God, you're going to be fined
$500. What happened was
he was held in contempt of of Congress.
He was found guilty,
fined $500. He went back to
headquarters,
and the old-timers told me that
every CIA employee had lined the halls,
and they were throwing dollars and five
dollars into a hat to pay the director's
$500 fine.
Just as a big FU to to Congress.
>> What caused that that Was it the the
shock of World War II when you still had
this culture that we're facing
existential threat from social communist
>> That's exactly what it was.
The it was the communist boogeyman.
Well, um also in 1960 I'm sorry, in
1975,
Senator Church and Congressman Pike
insisted
on an executive order that became known
as EO 12333.
Executive Order 12333 became the basis
for what the CIA was allowed to do
overseas and not allowed to do. And the
original draft the original version
signed version of 12333
forbade assassinations.
Okay?
Until September 12th, 2001.
And then President Bush kind of crossed
that part out and said, "Kill anybody
you want."
And that's what they've been doing ever
since.
>> Now, are these assassinations done by
the special activities group?
Are they like in the movies? Do they
poison people, have heart attacks,
commit suicide, or is it just
>> different kinds of things.
>> as in the movies?
>> Yeah, it is. It can be. I mean,
sometimes it's as crude as
you know, the guy's walking his dog.
This happened recently, I read in the
paper. Uh the guy's walking his dog, a
van pulls up alongside, the side door
opens, uh you get a bullet in your
brain, the door closes, and the van
drives off.
>> That's when they're sending a message.
They want people to know what happened.
>> Mhm.
Sometimes they'll kidnap a guy and then
nobody ever sees him again.
There There were times
when I was the executive assistant to
the CIA's Deputy Director
for operations.
After I got back from Pakistan, I got
promoted.
And the the Deputy Director made me his
assistant. In that position, you see
literally everything that the CIA is
doing everywhere in the world.
Compartments six levels above top
secret. It was ridiculous. I couldn't
even sleep at night.
But
you you see
I have to be careful with what I say
here. You see some some things that
you're like
what?
Why would we do that?
Right? We're a nation of laws or we're
not a nation of laws. You can't pretend
to be one while being the other.
If you don't like this guy's politics,
you can't just walk up to him and put a
bullet in his head.
You know, we we we would get these
cables like
oh, uh
yeah, we were uh interrogating this guy
uh during the night. And um
uh Jim may have gone a little too far,
but um
well, he's deceased now, so what should
we do?
And then the the geographic uh
office will write back, well, where are
you?
Well, we're next to the safe house.
Can you just bury him in the backyard?
Yeah, we'll just do that.
And they just dig a hole and bury the
guy.
And then years later, you see these
newspaper articles like, so-and-so's
family, they haven't heard from him in
years. He He was there one day and gone
the next. And like, where could he
possibly be? Uh I can tell you where he
is.
He's buried in the backyard of the safe
house.
But that's not a nation of laws. That's
not what a nation of laws does.
So, we're either going to be the good
guys or we're not going to be the good
guys. But we can't pretend to be one
while being the other.
>> And if we're not the good guys, we won't
be able to remain our
>> Oh, exactly.
>> position as the sole hegemon.
>> Exactly.
>> Because the rest of the world is wise to
us. And it's all going to collapse
around us.
>> They're wise to us now.
>> Yeah.
>> How do we What would your advice be to I
mean, you're looking at what's happening
in Lebanon right now. It's scandalous.
It's shocking. It's unimaginable.
And uh
it's just as if things are it's just You
know, I I have a different view of the
German people in the '30s and '40s.
Like, what could they have known?
We have phones bombarding us with
information every day. The Germans would
not have known what was happening in
Auschwitz or in the Eastern Front or in
Paris.
Um
but the American people have access to
this information. But they have rational
ignorance. So, I have to pick my kids up
from school. I have to My boss wants
this report. My wife wants me to make
more money. They're just thinking about
their life and they don't have time to
think about
the decimation of ancient Christian
cities, monasteries, churches, schools.
Um what if you were to sit down across
from President Trump and say, "This is
what you need to do
so we can reclaim and maintain
our position in the world?" What would
you say?
>> I think that he needs to put the
interests of the United States first,
above all else. We have succored our
foreign policy to Israel.
And Israel's security is not my concern
as an American. My concern is the
security of the United States of
America. And joining ourselves at the
hip with Israel is dragging us down. You
know, there was a You know The Onion?
The satirical I love The Onion, They had
a headline a couple weeks ago that just
really hit.
And it said um
China content to sit back and watch US
destroy itself.
Exactly.
Because that's what's happening.
We're destroying ourselves. Listen,
when when you have votes in the United
Nations General Assembly every single
year for the last 50 years and literally
the entire world is on one side and on
the other side is the US, Israel, Costa
Rica and Nauru.
There's a problem.
We're not smarter than everybody else in
the rest of the world every year.
Joining ourselves with the Israelis.
>> And it's undermining our interest in the
world.
>> It is. It's really undermining in the
When I went to Israel last time, 2022,
one thing I saw that at first perplexed
me and then just pissed me off.
When you you're in the old city in
Jerusalem and you're approaching the
Western Wall, right? There's like
a museum there and and some think tank
or whatever. People had put up these
signs, like glued these signs to the
walls and they said, "America, we are
with you."
It's like, what?
First [snorts] of all,
about what?
Secondly,
>> The size of Milwaukee.
>> Yeah. We don't want you with us.
>> What do you with us with uh yeah.
>> Yeah. It it hurts us that you're with
us.
We don't want you.
You can't live with civilized countries.
>> You just hit the nail on the head.
Though, I think the average like boomer,
me, who would have been me, even though
I'm a Gen Xer, to the Gen Z, anyone over
anyone who didn't have a smartphone in
their pocket during puberty is a boomer.
And I think that's a good designation
cuz it's true. They're different than
the rest of us.
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> And so as a typical boomer conservative
Republican, I would have if I would have
heard that 15 years ago before I had a
lot of experience in the region, I would
say, "What are you talking about?
They're the only civilized country in
the region." And I had this I had this
idea that they were
>> democracy in the Middle East.
>> that they were surrounded by all of
these just barbarians. And then you go
to Lebanon and Jordan and Iraq and Syria
and and and the Palestine and like these
are beautiful, deep And in the Middle
East, they're even very proud. They're
like, "We're not like the Gulf states.
We have a culture and a civilization."
>> And they do.
>> They do.
>> Yeah, they do. Like you have the Yazidi
that are the proto-Semitic people that
have been living in the same valleys
since Abraham left. Since Abraham left.
>> yes.
>> Christian communities praying in Aramaic
>> Yes.
>> where St. Thomas put a church.
>> Yes. Exactly.
>> And then you're going to watch the 700
Club or John Hagee and you're going to
preach theology to first-century
Christian communities in the Holy Land
that's ancestors were in the upper room.
>> Yeah. That's exactly right.
>> So, what would you say to the boomer
Republican who's been
watching 700 Club since the '90s,
watching Pastor Hagee, watching Fox
News, they just can't hear it?
>> Read the history. You've got to open
your mind to the history.
Don't believe some guy yapping at you on
your TV.
You have to read and understand the
history.
It really is as simple as that.
But people do what's expedient. It's It
takes time and it's hard and maybe it's
boring and
but you've got Read the early church
fathers.
>> Just go there. Keep your
mouth shut.
>> That's that's a great idea.
>> from Bethlehem to Taybeh
>> Mhm.
>> That's a great idea.
>> forever.
>> I couldn't agree more.
>> This is the last Gen Z question, which I
really love. What beliefs did you hold
strongly at 30 that you no longer
believe today?
>> Oh, that's a good
>> the way, you're an Angry Birds legend.
This is from Colin.
>> I live I live Angry Birds.
>> By the way, that's something my kids
loved about. She's like, "Dad, like he
just talks about his love for Angry
Birds. [laughter] It's like, who does
that? That is so cool." But, it's that
kind of transparency and honesty
>> [laughter]
>> that you were like reflect I needed you
I needed to play Angry Birds. This is
what makes me happy. This is what I do.
>> It brings me joy in the morning.
>> you joy.
>> Yeah.
>> I love it.
>> I I have a routine in the morning. This
is apropos of nothing, but
I have a routine in the morning. I play
Angry Birds. That takes about an hour,
50 minutes. I play the daily uh
solitaire, just cuz I have a streak that
I don't want to break. But, my doctor
told me
to do the New York Times crossword
puzzle every day because it actually
does fend off, you know,
the degeneration of the brain. And I
don't want like I don't have
dementia in my family on either side,
but just to be on the safe side, I want
to keep my brain fresh. So, I do the
Washington Post crossword, the New York
Times crossword, the uh USA Today
crossword if I have the time, Angry
Birds and solitaire.
>> challenging of the crosswords?
>> Times.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
Especially Saturday. Saturday's way
harder than Sunday.
>> pros.
>> Oh, yeah. Saturday's tough. Like I I'm
2/3 done with today's. It's hard.
But, anyway,
um
what do I not believe now that I
believed at 30? That we are just
unequivocally the good guys.
It's just not true.
It's not. I also believed
I used to say all the time, "I want my
leaders to be smarter than I am."
Right? To make wise decisions.
And I've I've come to realize they're
just human beings, and most of them
aren't smarter than the rest of us.
They're just more political and, you
know,
found themselves in positions of power.
Um
>> They have the same nervous system, the
same bandwidth, the same
>> Yeah, I'll I'll tell Yeah,
[clears throat] they do. I'll tell you a
story. When I was when I was in college
um I I was very fortunate to win this
thing called the Lyndon B. Johnson
Congressional Scholarship
or internship. So, it was the only paid
internship on Capitol Hill. And I worked
for my Congressman. He was a
conservative Democrat from Western
Pennsylvania, pro-life, pro-gun,
pro-labor, you know, the old old school
Democrat.
And um I liked the guy a lot.
I sat next to the press secretary who
was this really, really good-looking.
She'd been Miss Iowa of all things. And
she was dating an Exxon lobbyist. He was
a great guy, too. See, he'd come and
hang out in the office all the time. One
day, the Congressman comes in.
I'm only saying this cuz he died
recently. So, he can't like sue me or
anything.
But the Congressman comes in one day and
he goes like this. He goes, "I got laid
last night."
>> [laughter]
>> And I said,
"No, he didn't. Mrs. Coulter's not even
in Washington. She's in Pittsburgh."
And I was like,
>> [sighs]
>> And the lobbyist said to me, "You see,
they're all dogs. They all put their
pants on one leg at a time, just like
you do, and they're all dogs who think
that they're better than everybody
else." He said, "I don't know why you
idolize these guys."
And he was right.
He was right.
I went into
I went into see um
the Assistant Secretary of State one
time.
He had He called me and asked me to come
over to a
He wanted a briefing on this really like
obscure issue dealing with the Gulf.
So, I went in.
And um
he said, "You know, I was at the White
House the other day
in this
mutual colleague's office.
And I saw a picture
on his desk with that friend of yours."
I said, "What friend of mine?"
"That woman you sit next to."
I said, "What are you talking about?"
He said, "The director
has a picture of himself with the woman
you sit next to."
I said, "They're They're both married."
And I was like, "Oh, for heaven's sake."
>> And they don't even It's not even
>> And next thing you know, they both get
divorced, they marry each other. It's
like, you know, it's Peyton Place over
here. We used to have this joke at the
CIA.
That when you go into a conference
a conference room, never touch the table
cuz you don't know who was having sex on
it last night.
And it was serious.
In 2004, 2003
um
we had to send doctors from the Office
of Medical Services out to Iraq
because CIA officers were passing around
a CIA specific strain of gonorrhea
amongst each other.
It was seen only in CIA officers.
And the doctors are like, "Can't you
people control yourselves?"
>> got caught on the top of the embassy
having sex.
>> did.
>> This And that guy is an animal. I'd love
to do a documentary exposé on him.
>> You and I should chat about that after
this. I got some stuff to tell you.
>> I mean, that guy And And when I would
when I was in Iraq documenting the
genocide the Peshmerga and I'd meet with
senior leadership and I'd meet with
generals. I'd meet too. But they'd all
have US Embassy stories.
>> Yeah. Cuz they're all pigs.
>> They're pigs. They talk about they
they'd have to get a shuttle because
they were so drunk, they couldn't even
So this is why I don't have empathy for
them.
Um
I I have to imagine if they're engaged
in high-risk adultery in front of
everyone at the office.
>> you.
>> That they have existential angst,
they're lonely, they're despairing, and
they just want to that this is kind of
tragic. So, it's a culture of tragically
lonely people, which then if I was a
foreign
if I was another intelligence agency, no
one's easier for me to recruit than
someone who's lonely and alienated.
>> all lonely and alienated alienated. Let
me tell you,
my deputy director that I worked for had
been married five times. And all five of
his wives had first been his secretary.
All five [snorts] of them. I'll give you
another example.
When I was working in Pakistan,
um I was dating
a senior CIA officer who became my wife.
So, we were just dating at the time. I
had just gotten divorced.
And um we had this uh trunk line in the
in the station. So, even though I was in
Pakistan, I could pick up that phone and
it was a local Washington, D.C. number.
So, we were 11 and 1/2 hours ahead. So,
when I'd get to the office at 7:00, I
would call her at 7:30 the previous
evening in Washington.
And we would just talk about how our day
was.
So, one of the guys in my
office, I had seven old-timers
um working for me. They had all been
either director or deputy director of
Near East operations, and they came back
after 9/11 just for patriotic reasons.
But if you're a contractor, you can't
lead a group. So, I was the chief of the
group, and all of these senior
intelligence service officers were
working for me, which was a great
blessing for me. I learned more from
them than I learned over the rest of the
course of my career.
>> And these were men that came up in the
when it was all on on the line.
>> The yeah, the battle days.
So,
my girlfriend and I would end each
conversation with, "Okay, love you.
Mwah." and hang up.
And one of them heard me.
And he says, "So, are there wedding
bells in the future?" And I said, "Oh, I
don't know. I I just got divorced. I'm
kind of afraid of being a two-time
loser." That's what I said, two-time
loser.
He says, "Two-time loser?
I've been married four times. Dave, how
many times have you been married?" He
says, "Five for me. Bill, how many times
have you been married? I got three.
Frank, how many times have you been
married? Four for me. He says, two-time
loser. Kid, you're just getting started,
he says to me.
And I said, oh my god, I don't want to
be like you guys.
I get home.
We get married.
And
one night
we're sitting on the floor of the living
room watching a movie. It's like
midnight. We're watching this movie and
her cell phone rings and it happened to
be next to me.
I picked it up and I said, it's like a
16-digit number. I said to her, I think
it's a sat phone.
And she says, answer it. See who it is.
So I said, hello.
And this voice says,
is Heather there?
And I said,
Tony?
And he said, yeah, who's this? I said,
it's John. Where are you?
He said, I'm in Afghanistan.
And he said,
he said, why are you answering Heather's
phone?
I said,
cuz she's my wife.
Why are you calling Heather's phone at
midnight? Oh, he goes, I'm sorry. I
didn't realize that you two were
together. I said, Tony, why don't you
use your 1 minute of sat time every week
to call your own wife
instead of calling mine.
But that's typical of the CIA.
They don't care. And that's a problem in
marriage.
>> And the culture, that should be seen as
a real security problem.
>> for these two guys.
I loved and respected both of them, Mike
and Gene.
Two of the finest officers I ever worked
for.
And they hated each other.
So one day I said to Gene,
I said, Gene, you and Mike are both
you're two of my favorite people. I
don't understand why you hate each other
so much.
And Gene says, I'll I'll you.
He said, our first tour together, we
were in Karachi and Mike screwed my
wife." I said, "Oh my god, that's
terrible. I'm so sorry to hear that."
And he said, "No, that's okay." He said,
uh,
"Our second tour was Bogota and I
screwed his wife."
And I said, "You know, this is exactly
what's wrong with this organization." I
said, "Shame on both of you."
>> By the way, am I that naive? I just
think if I'm wanting to recruit
somebody, I want to recruit someone
who's just betrayed by someone in his
own organization in such a horrible way.
>> Exactly right. Talk about a
vulnerability.
>> like quite a vulnerability. Then you
have a culture like this where Brett
McGurk is on the top of the embassy, the
whole Middle East knows. The whole
Middle East
>> in charge of the war against ISIS. That
seems kind of uh
>> You're exactly right.
>> It seems like a problem that needs to be
fixed.
>> Amen.
>> I I could talk to you forever. I don't
know how much time we have, but
that's the next question. What How do we
fix the culture of CIA to serve the
interests of the American people? Can it
be fixed or does it have to be shattered
[snorts] and swept away?
>> only way it can be fixed is with true,
robust congressional oversight, which we
have not seen since 1982.
>> Can we see it when we know the ethics of
guys that have to get elected every 2
years?
>> No, I don't think so.
I mean, Mark Warner, Tom Cotton,
come on.
These guys?
>> Randy Fine?
>> Randy Fine? Please. What a joke.
It's all a big joke.
I I've I've said in podcasts in the
past,
there was one guy
on uh on the Senate Intelligence
Committee
that I kind of expected a little help
from.
And when I got out of prison, I was
invited to dinner at the Greek
Ambassador's residence. So, I go and
this senator's there, member of the
Intelligence Committee. And he comes up
to me and he says, he says, "Hey,
welcome home. Congratulations. We were
really worried about you."
And I said, "Oh, come on, Senator.
I said, I expected more from you. You of
all people, I expected a little bit of
support." And he goes, "Look,
it took everything I had just to not
lose my security clearance.
And I said, "Oh, you're afraid of them."
Now it makes sense to me.
And we've never spoken again.
>> He's He was never a free man.
>> No, never. He's afraid of them.
>> You know, one of my favorite stanzas and
lines in any poem is in Rudyard
Kipling's If.
And I was just talking to my son about
this and actually talking about you.
It is if when all if all men can count
on you, but none too much, you're a man.
And I said to my son,
"Do you know what that Do you understand
what that means?" He says, "Yeah, that's
your just."
That you put justice and truth over
friendship and loyalty. I said, "Yes." I
said, "Now let me ask you a question.
If anyone if one person in this world
can count on you too much,
then can anyone count on you at all?"
>> There it is.
>> And that's the reality.
>> I want to ask a hypothetical question of
the folks that are here.
This is something that I like to raise
at
at colleges and universities. Because
it's kind of indicative of what every
CIA officer has to deal with. Especially
if you're a field officer, you're out
doing operations. So,
let's say that you're a CIA case officer
in the Middle East.
And you've recruited a bonafide
terrorist, a bonafide penetration of
Al-Qaeda, Hezbollah, ISIS, whatever it
is. It doesn't matter. You meet with
this person once a month in a hotel
somewhere in the Middle East.
And this person has given you actionable
intelligence that you have used
to disrupt attacks and save American
lives, right?
He's the real deal.
So, you go out to Amman or Cairo to do a
meeting and he says to you, "I've been
good to you and I've given you
everything that you've wanted. So,
tonight you're going to do something for
me. I'm not giving you any more
information until you go out and get me
a prostitute. So, I always ask, do you
get him the prostitute? Show of hands.
Right?
Seriously, show Would you get him the
prostitute?
Yeah, the answer is yeah.
It's nasty and dirty, but this is the
job that we've chosen.
You get him the prostitute.
What if he asks you for a child
prostitute?
Well, obviously the answer is absolutely
not. Not under any circumstances. But,
that's not even the issue. The issue is
there are no rules.
There's no training class to say, well,
you know, you can get him the
prostitute, but you can't get him the
child prostitute because there's this
line. Nobody's going to teach you that.
So, you have to go into this job,
into this life, with your own set of
moral principles.
And you have to stick with it.
Because there's not going to be anybody
at the other side of the the other end
of the cable at headquarters saying,
"Uh, you probably shouldn't do that."
Or, "Rule number 125A says yes to the
prostitute, but no to the child
prostitute."
It's all up to you.
And so, you know, so many guys
and women,
mostly guys, lose the sense
of who they are
once they get into this position.
And once it's lost, you can't reclaim
it.
>> Thank you for that. Okay, I want to end
on a kind of a happy note. You are
record-setting at Cameo right now.
>> I know, it's crazy, right?
>> is where you you it's a service where
you can get a famous person to give
someone a birthday wish or something
like this. And you are like setting
Cameo records.
>> all the Cameo records.
>> You've broken all the Cameo records.
>> [laughter]
>> And um when we first we're talking about
having you on my film, you're like, "I'd
love a line in your film." So, and I'm
like, "Yeah, quite. I'd love you in my
film for your SAG card. You don't need
that anymore. You've well blown past
that.
>> card.
>> So, you you how many hours a week are
you leaving messages?
>> Just answering Cameo requests, I'm doing
probably
25 or 30 hours a week.
>> So, that's how many Cameos a week?
>> I did 900 for the month of March.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay, so what we want I want to know is
of all these Cameos
what was the sweetest one?
>> Uh
I've gotten three. I've I've done about
1,950 Cameos so far.
>> Okay.
>> I do 20 or 30 a day.
>> I've gotten three where Well, let me let
me back up. About 50% of them are
birthday wishes. You know,
uh Jimbo's birthday is next Tuesday. I
say, "Hey, happy birthday Jimbo. John
Kiriakou here. Hope you had a great day,
you know, etc."
So, there's birthday, you know, Mother's
Day, Father's Day, whatever.
Advice.
Pep talk.
About 10% are pep talks.
So, of the 10% that have been pep talks,
three
have come back to say that I somehow
talked them out of committing suicide.
I'm not really sure how I did that.
But you know, there are a lot of really
hurting people out there.
We get so wrapped up in our own lives,
our own existences, we don't realize how
many other people are in pain.
There's one girl, she's just one out of
almost 2,000 Cameos that I've done.
One who sounded like she was in such
pain. I said, "Listen." In the Cameo, I
said,
"We're not supposed to do this, but
here's my phone number."
>> Wow.
>> "Call me."
And she called me.
Crying, she's 15.
She's bulimic.
Her parents don't understand her. She
was going to commit suicide.
And I talked her out of it.
And um she's called me twice since then.
Usually for less than a minute or two.
>> Very respectful.
>> Very, very respectful. And she said she
just she's having a down day and she
needs to hear a friendly voice.
And that's it. I had another friend.
Friend.
Um
he became a friend. So
I get it I get an a message through
Facebook. The guy says, "Hi, my name is
James.
And I want to thank you for what you did
for the country."
So I look at his page and here's picture
after picture after picture of him
embedded with the Syrian Kurds fighting
ISIS.
And I was like, "Wow." I said, "Thank
you. Thank you for what you did." I
said, "The Kurds are heroic. I've loved
the Kurds all of my adult life since I
first you know started working with the
Iraqi Kurds in northern Iraq."
And we became friends. This guy had the
most tragic story.
His mother was a prostitute.
And he was born with fetal alcohol
syndrome.
So
never had any idea who his father was.
And when he was 17 he he did something
really, really stupid.
He kidnapped a guy at gunpoint
and took him from ATM to ATM forcing him
to empty his bank account.
And of course he got caught.
And the judge came down on him like a
ton of bricks. Gave him 20 years.
And he did the whole 20.
Well, he gets out he's 37 years old.
He's got a violent felony on his record.
Employment is impossible.
So he goes into porn. It's the only
thing he can do. He acts in porn. And
what do you make in porn? I don't know,
$150? Who knows?
So,
he decides he he needs meaning in his
life.
So, he goes to Turkey, crosses the
border into Syria, stumbles into these
Kurds, takes up arms, and just starts
killing ISIS people.
He does that for a year,
and then comes back out, makes his way
back to the United States, Billings,
Montana.
So,
we start talking, and he can't find a
job, and I'm a convicted felon, and I
have this
this uh
violent felony, and I don't have any
education, and
he didn't have anything going for him.
And I kept telling him,
"One day at a time.
Go to the local community college.
What's a community college class cost?
$100? $150? Whatever you're interested
in,
you know? Whatever Whatever, you know,
tickles your fancy, focus on that. Just
one day at a time." I'm telling him.
Then one day,
I get a call on my phone, and it says
prison/jail.
And it has some Wyoming
Wyoming area code. I'm like, "What in
the world?" So, I answer the phone, and
it's him. I said, "What in the world are
you doing in jail in Wyoming?"
He said, "I got into a fight with my
girlfriend, and she wouldn't let me see
my son, and I slapped her, and she
uh had me arrested." I said, "Geez,
James."
So, he ends up getting bail,
and then decides he's going to commit
suicide. So, he goes back home in
Billings, Montana,
takes a gun from his mother, drives to
the Walmart parking lot.
He's sitting in the car holding the gun,
getting ready to kill himself
when an off-duty ATF agent pulls into
the space next to him to do his grocery
shopping.
Sees this guy with a gun, pulls his gun,
and disarms James.
So, I get a call, Billings, Montana
County Jail. I was like, you've got to
be kidding me. So, I answer. I said,
James,
you're in jail in Billings, Montana now?
He says, he's crying. I was going to
kill myself. I was in the parking lot at
the Walmart. I said, oh my god.
He said, I need a I need an attorney. I
said, all right, cuz I'm a sucker for a
sob story. I always have been. So, I
start calling every attorney in
Billings, Montana.
And I find one that's willing to do it,
you know, for a price.
So, he gets him out, but felon with a
gun is a mandatory minimum of 5 years.
The The court's are or the prosecutor's
asking for 8 years because he had a
violent felony, and this is bad.
Then he calls me one day, July 4th,
2022,
and he said,
hey, my sister
uh lit an M80, and it blew three of her
fingers off, and she was in surgery all
day, 14 hours, they reattached her
fingers. I said, oh my god, that's
terrible, James. I'm so sorry. Tell her
I send my best. I'll send her a card.
And I said, but you sound you sound
good. He said, yeah, I feel good. I feel
[clears throat] good. Things are going
well. I said, great. Okay, good to talk
to you.
Two days later, his sister calls me.
I said, how are your fingers? She said,
oh, they're okay. It was my own stupid
fault, but they reattached them. I'll
recover. And she said, but that's not
why I'm calling. I'm calling to tell you
James killed himself last night.
I said, oh my god.
What happened?
And she said, um
he told their mother he was going for a
walk.
He walked to the neighbor's house or
yard. They had a big oak tree.
And he strung up a noose
and he hung himself.
And he left a note.
And all it said was, "Please call John
and tell him I said I was sorry."
And you know, it reminded me of a story.
Have any of you heard of the folk singer
Pete Seeger?
Pete was a giant in my life. Next to my
father and my grandfather, no man had as
much of an impact on my life as Pete
Seeger did.
And he told me a story one time. There
was another folk singer from the '70s,
Phil Ochs.
Um Phil was as popular as anybody in the
'60s and early '70s. But he went on a
concert tour in Africa and he was mugged
in Africa and the mugger cut his throat.
And he recovered, but he was unable to
hit high notes after that and he fell
into a deep depression.
And Pete told me
that that he, Pete, was performing at a
folk club in Greenwich Village one night
and the gig ran late.
And he was packing up as quickly as he
could because he had to literally run to
Grand Central Station and catch the last
train to Beacon, which is where his home
was.
And as he's packing up, one of the
waitresses Pete, Phil Ochs is on the
phone for you.
And he said,
"Tell Phil I can't talk. I have to run
and get the last train to Beacon."
And so he said, "Tell him I'll call him
tomorrow."
And he left and Phil Ochs committed
suicide.
And he said to me, and this was unlike a
anything I had ever heard Pete say,
he said, "That selfish bastard.
I'll never forgive him for what he did.
He had no idea how many people he's
hurt."
And that always stuck in my mind.
>> Mhm.
>> In your dark days.
>> Very well may have.
Absolutely. suicide?
So you saved your life
and you saved a 15-year-old girl's life.
There [clears throat] it is. So when you
were going through all the rough things
that you went through and your brother
told you this is the best thing that
ever happened to your life, he didn't
realize it was the best thing that was
going to happen to a lot of people's
lives.
>> Yeah.
It's true.
We're all here for a reason and it just
keeps reminding me that there's always
somebody who's suffering more than I am.
And the privilege of suffering is
you'll be able to use that empathy to
help someone else another time. You lose
your child to a drunk driver, there's
going to come a day where
you're helping someone who lost their
child too. There's that's the empathy is
the gift of suffering.
>> That's right.
>> And so it's interesting that we must
have a suffering nation cuz they really
identified with you. You really done the
whole arc of the hero's journey.
You're You know that your call to
adventure was not when you thought. It
wasn't when you joined CIA. It's when
you the moment your adventure began was
the moment you said
>> And who would have thought? Who could
have foreseen that? I never could have.
I would have never believed you if you
had told me, "Listen, in the next 10
years, this is what's going to happen."
>> [cough]
>> I think when we first met if I would
have told you that. Oh well, you didn't
believe me. Jenny and I were like,
"Look, we're passing on your movie
because we are this is
a massive studio film. This is the
perfect script. It It you wrote it in
your life."
Like you literally hit each of the
points
>> [laughter]
>> of the monomyth in your life.
And then you were discovered
by young people.
>> Which is the greatest reward.
It really is.
>> You know, when you were
you were walking down the street to a
book reading and I called you
and when I was asking you to do this, I
think. I like, "This is kind of an
unbelievable opportunity. I don't know
[laughter] if you can do this and I
thought there was no way you could fit
in your schedule.
And you're like, "Yeah, yeah, yeah." But
as you're walking to the book reading,
someone you could hear how excited they
were
>> [laughter]
>> to see you, but then you seemed more
excited
to see thank him. And you said, "If not
for you, I could be living out of my
car. If not for Gen Z, in a way, you
would have a whole fight ahead of you."
>> Yeah.
>> A whole life of battles.
>> It's true.
It's true.
Yeah.
The CIA did
its darnedest to make sure I could never
work again.
>> Wah, wah. Didn't work.
>> Didn't work.
>> I mean, here's how bad things got. And
I'm not saying that this is bad. I mean,
maybe in the greater scheme of things
it's bad, but I was so broke and so
unemployable,
I had to I had to rent a house with two
elderly gay guys
who were attached to oxygen machines,
walking around like smoking cigarettes
with their oxygen
>> This is in the middle of the night.
>> "So, this is my lot in life."
>> you watching? Wheel of Fortune? What
were they watching?
>> know, right?
>> I don't know.
>> Jeopardy at 7:00 and Wheel of Fortune at
7:30. And I'm sitting there like this.
[laughter]
Yeah. Like, well, I guess this is the
way it's going to be.
And then everything exploded.
>> But that's what here it was and looks
like. It's not uh
you know, it's not the Rambo stuff. It's
the long drawn out years and years of
not thinking it's going to get better.
>> Mhm.
>> Was there a point where you just said,
"I'm I'm good. It's going to be like
this forever and I can handle it."
>> Yeah. It was a conversation I had with
my sister.
I said, "You know, I don't mind being
poor.
I've actually become accustomed to being
And um I said, "The only thing is I
don't want to die alone."
And I especially don't want to be sick
for a whole long time before dying
alone.
My sister's 5 years younger than I am
and she's very, very kind and
empathetic. She's my best friend,
really.
And she said, "Don't be ridiculous.
You're going to You're going to live in
my house." She said, "The whole
The whole basement, it's this beautiful
apartment." They have an enormous house
in Bedford, New Hampshire.
And I said,
"Great.
I get to live in my sister's basement
for my remaining days.
Thanks, Tina."
>> [laughter]
>> You know, my organization runs a shelter
in Juarez, Mexico
>> Even better.
>> for migrant workers for for migrant
unwed migrant unaccompanied women with
children. So, we have a shelter there.
And the shelter director [laughter]
said, "If I have in my old days, if I
have nowhere to go, they'll let me in
the shelter in Juarez. You can come to
the shelter in Juarez with me."
No, okay. So, I want to end on this. And
then we'll go to questions. And then
we'll decide with the audience. I don't
know if they want to be in the in the
video or not, but
um I want to pay a Cameo. How much does
a Cameo cost? I want to buy a Cameo
right now.
>> Hey, thank you.
You know, the algorithm changes the
price every 15 minutes based on how uh
>> how much demand
>> cash so we don't have to share with the
website. No, we'll kick it to you. No,
so this is my Cameo, right? I want to do
it right now.
>> Here's my Cameo. To Gen Z, I want you to
give them a Cameo pep talk to a
generation that they want to be creative
writers, they want to be filmmakers,
they want to be lawyers, and they're
looking at AI and that's gone. They want
to have marriage and love and family,
but that seems impossible. So, I want
you to give Gen Z your Cameo pep talk.
>> Yeah. Okay, Gen Z.
John Kiriakou here. Listen, I know how
hard life is right now.
You're seeing changes coming quicker
than we've ever seen really since the
since the advent of the industrial age,
and that's not necessarily a good thing.
So, what you have to do is grab life by
the horns and live it according to your
standards. Don't let AI put you out of
business. Don't let
internet porn take away a chance at a at
a beautiful relationship or marriage.
You have to grab life by the horns and
live it according to your own rules.
So, do what makes you happy, do what
allows you to contribute to society, and
you're going to live a happy life.
All the best.
>> That was awesome. John, I want to thank
you. You know, um I wanted to just thank
you so much for your example. You
personally inspired my son. You're
inspiring a generation. Thank you very
much, brother.
>> Thank you.
>> All right, guys. Jason Jones here, back
at my studio. What an incredible
opportunity to interview John Kiriakou.
Couldn't do my outro after the interview
because, as you can see, we had a lot of
folks, had to mingle, and it was kind of
loud.
So, I just want to say, thank you for
listening to the end to the end of this
show. And if you want to hear more, we
have about an hour and a half of Q&A
with John and the audience.
But, that is only going to be available
to paid subscribers. It's $8 a month. To
paid subscribers for the Jason Jones
show Substack. It is in the show notes.
So, click through there, become a paid
subscriber, and next week we're going to
release the hour and a half of Q&A. And
a lot of these questions came from Gen
Z, and they had some incredible
questions, and John's answers were
mind-blowing. We talked about aliens, we
talked about all kinds of Kennedy
assassination, all kinds of interesting
questions.
Um also, [snorts] this episode, like all
of our episodes, is brought to you by
the Vulnerable People Project, standing
in solidarity with the most vulnerable
people in the world when the world has
walked away. Go to our website,
vulnerablepeopleproject.com,
and look at the work that we do. Go to
savewestbankchristians.com
and sign our statement of support for
Palestinian Christians, for Christians
in the Holy Land. If you want to be a
part of our work, you can go to either
two of those websites, and they're both
in the show notes, and become a monthly
donor. It's the monthly donors that give
us the courage to grow our work. The
beginning of the year, our goal was to
reach 100 Christian communities that
have protection in Nigeria schools,
churches, hospitals. We're now up to 54
Christian institutions and the only
synagogue in Nigeria that's left we
provide security for. You can look at
our work that we do around the world
providing prosthetic limbs in Gaza for
children, our work to keep the Christian
community in the West Bank, and our work
in India, China, and around the world.
So, go to savewestbankchristians.com,
vulnerablepeopleproject.com,
and become a part of the team. Go into
the show notes and also subscribe,
become a monthly subscriber to the Jason
Jones Show Substack, and you can check
out those
>> [music]
>> an hour and a half of Q&A with John
Kiriakou. All right, guys, until next
time.
Jason Jones Show.
>> [music]